<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Speculem Sherlockianum, or, A looking-glass in which the admirers of Mr. Sherlock may behold the man, as to his accuracy, judgement, orthodoxy by an obedient son of the Church of England.</title>
            <author>Hickman, Henry, d. 1692.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1674</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 121 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 36 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A43720</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H1916</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R10759</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12198952</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12198952</idno>
            <idno type="VID">56069</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A43720)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 56069)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 763:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Speculem Sherlockianum, or, A looking-glass in which the admirers of Mr. Sherlock may behold the man, as to his accuracy, judgement, orthodoxy by an obedient son of the Church of England.</title>
                  <author>Hickman, Henry, d. 1692.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 68, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Thomas Parkhurst ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1674.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Duke University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jesus Christ.</term>
               <term>Sherlock, William, 1641?-1707. --  Discourse concerning the knowledge of Jesus Christ.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:56069:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:56069:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Speculum Sherlockianum:</hi> OR, A LOOKING-GLASS In which the ADMIRERS of M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> Sherlock may behold the Man, as to his Accuracy, Judgement, Orthodoxy.</p>
            <p>By an Obedient Son of the Church of <hi>ENGLAND.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Parkhurſt</hi> at the Three Crowns and Bible at the lower end of <hi>Cheap-ſide,</hi> near <hi>Mercers-Chappell,</hi> M.DC.LXXIV.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:56069:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:56069:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>YOu are pleaſed in your Letter <hi>March</hi> 24th, to counſel me to buy the Book called, <hi>A Diſcourſe concerning the Knowledge of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> not queſtioning but by reading of it, I ſhall be brought to abate of the eſteem I have ſometime expreſſed of thoſe Divines who are therein refuted. Your counſel to buy the Book came ſomewhat too late, I had bought it ſundry weeks before, tempted ſo to do by its promiſing title and flattering my ſelf into a perſwaſion, that what was written by Mr. <hi>W. S.</hi> and Licenſed by Dr. <hi>S. P.</hi> muſt needs contain in it ſomewhat extraordinary. In this perſwaſion I was ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what confirmed, becauſe I found the Author in the Preface averring that he had compoſed his Book not without imploring the guidance and direction of God. But having peruſed only his firſt Chapter, conſiſting of 13 pages; I found in them ſo much weakneſs, contradiction, and calumny, that I wiſh'd I had the Money I gave for the Book in my Pocket again.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 3. He ſaith, <q>The Goſpel of Chriſt is as ſevere a diſpenſation as the Law which dooms all men to eternal miſery, who live not very innocent and virtuous lives, but the Perſon of Chriſt is all Grace, a meer refuge for the wicked and ungodly.</q>
            </p>
            <p>If theſe words expreſs his own mind, then have thoſe who ordained him, reaſon to wiſh they had laid their hands upon a thorn buſh, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:56069:3"/> than impoſed them on his head. If they are intended to repreſent the opinion of others whom he takes upon him to refute, or rather to deride, then muſt I needs for the preſent, look upon them as a calumny, being very con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident that no one of them hath either Preached or Printed ſuch things from which ſuch deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate abſurd opinions can be inferred.</p>
            <p>Pag. 4. <hi>Some men wherever they meet with the word Chriſt in Scripture, alwayes underſtand by it the Perſon of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have heard of ſome, that wherever they heard their Miniſter read the word <hi>Jeſus</hi> in the New Teſtament, thought they were to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand by it, the <hi>Redeemer of Mankind,</hi> and therefore have devoutly bowed their Knees at the Name <hi>Jeſus,</hi> when it ſignifyed <hi>Joſhua,</hi> or him that was called <hi>Justus;</hi> but of any men who thought that the word Chriſt was alwayes in the New Teſtament to be underſtood of the <hi>Perſon of Chriſt,</hi> did I never till I read this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor here, and I believe he himſelf doth not think there are any ſuch; if he do, why then doth he ſay <hi>pag.</hi> 11. that it is acknowledged by all, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſometimes ſignifyes the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Chriſt.</hi> Let us frame a Syllogiſm, If it be acknowledged by all that the word <hi>Chriſt</hi> doth ſometimes ſignifie <hi>the Church,</hi> then are there none who wherever they meet with the word <hi>Chriſt</hi> in Scripture, do alwayes underſtand it of the <hi>Perſon of Christ.</hi> But it is acknowledged by all, <hi>&amp;c. Ergo,</hi> If you can anſwer this Syl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logiſm, ſo as not to make your friend either to contradict himſelf, or calumniate others, then
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:56069:3"/> ſhall I confeſs my ſelf to be what you imagine, ſomewhat Melancholly, and to need a diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
            <p>Ibid. <hi>Chriſt is originally the name of an Office which the Jews call the Meſſias, or one anointed by God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That a concrete or connotative term ſhould be <hi>originally the name of an Office,</hi> ſeems to me very ſtrange and uncouth. All terms that are denominative, ſignifie two things; that which is denominated, and the form from which it is denominated; ſo muſt the word <hi>Chriſt</hi> needs ſignifie, and I deſpair of being referred to any place of Scripture where it ſignifies <hi>an Office,</hi> and not alſo <hi>the Perſon inveſted with the Office.</hi> But to ſay that the Jews call an Office the <hi>Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſias</hi> (a word of a Greek termination) or one anointed by God, is to father ſuch a piece of prodigious Nonſence upon the Jews, as I dare ſay they would be loth to have laid at their doors. And yet this confident Gentleman takes upon him to give a reaſon of ſo groſs Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence in theſe words, <hi>For under the Law, their Prophets, Prieſts, and Kings, were inveſted in their ſeveral Offices by the Ceremony of anointing them with Oyle.</hi> I will not be ſo ſevere as to bring this reaſon into the form of an argumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, leſt it ſhould create ſome horror in you: Make the words an intire or abſolute Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and you will not much fancy it; for indeed under the Law the <hi>High-Prieſts</hi> in regular times were <hi>inveſted in their Office, with the Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of anointing with Oyle;</hi> but ſo were not the <hi>inferiour Priests</hi> at any time ſave only the firſt.
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:56069:4"/> As for the <hi>Prophets</hi> under the Law, I cannot find that any one of them was <hi>inveſted in his Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical Office by the Ceremony of anointing with Oyle:</hi> which notwithſtanding, they might and perhaps were called, <hi>the Lords anointed,</hi> and ſo at this day may we call all Miniſters and Chriſtians, yet not becauſe they are anointed with Oyle ceremonially applyed to them when firſt they are put into the number of Miniſters or Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>He adds, <hi>That the legal unctions were typical of that divine unction the Holy Jeſus received at his baptiſm when the Spirit of God deſcended on him like a Dove,</hi> and I think that <hi>thoſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions were typical,</hi> but doubt many of the <hi>Jews</hi> never underſtood their <hi>typicalneſs,</hi> and do not ſee why they ſhould be thought only to have typi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied the <hi>anointing of Chriſt at his baptiſm.</hi> He was <hi>anointed with the Holy Ghoſt, and with power at his conception or incarnation.</hi> But be this as it will, I am unſatisfied with what follows <hi>page</hi> the 5th. <hi>That Gods anointing Chriſt with the Holy Ghoſt, and with power, ſhould be his conſecration to the Mediatory Office.</hi> Dr. <hi>Jack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> and Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi> ſing quite another Song, and tell us <hi>Chriſt was conſecrated to his Prieſtly Office</hi> (a part ſure of his Mediatory Office) <hi>by his ſufferings and death,</hi> and ſurely <hi>Chriſt's dying,</hi> was not his <hi>being anointed with the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> There follows ſomething <hi>pag.</hi> the 5th. which amazed me, for he ſaith <hi>all thoſe Offices of Prophet, Prieſt, and King, are not properly diſtinct Offices in Chriſt, but the ſeveral parts and adminiſtrations of his Mediatory Kingdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:56069:4"/>
            <p>Do not wonder if this put me into a little amaze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for reſolving it into three Propoſitions, I found every one of them ſtrange. 'Tis ſtrange preſumption for a young Divine to ſay, that <hi>theſe Offices are not diſtinct Offices in Chriſt,</hi> and never in the leaſt to ſuggeſt wherein the impropriety of ſo calling them doth lye. To find fault with forms of ſpeech generally uſed, and which may be retained without any inconvenience, and never to tell us where the faultineſs of thoſe forms of ſpeech lyes, does not become one who is minded to keep up a reputation of modeſty. The ſecond Propoſition is yet more ſtrange, <hi>theſe Offices are not diſtinct Offices, but the ſeveral parts of Chriſt's Mediatory Kingdom,</hi> as if they might not be diſtinct Offices, and yet parts. The third Propoſition is yet ſtrangeſt of all, <hi>That theſe Offices are the ſeveral administra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Christ's Mediatory Kingdom.</hi> Is an <hi>Office</hi> an <hi>administration?</hi> Is the <hi>Office</hi> of a King but one <hi>part</hi> and <hi>administration</hi> of a Mediatory Kingdom? You are wiſer than I, wherefore put me out of my wondering humour, and tell me what kind of <hi>totum</hi> a Mediatory Kingdom is to the <hi>Offices</hi> of <hi>Prophet, Prieſt,</hi> and <hi>King.</hi> And yet ſhould you ſo do, I ſhould not be cured of the admiring humour this Author hath put me into; for he tells me, ibid. <hi>That Christ's preaching of the Goſpel was his exerciſe of his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal Power and Authority in publiſhing his Laws, and the conditions of eternal life.</hi> I can eaſily underſtand, that <hi>to make and enact the Laws and conditions of eternal life, is an exerciſe of regal Power and Authority.</hi> So is it alſo to conſtitute
<pb facs="tcp:56069:5"/> and make Officers to promulge and publiſh Laws. But if bare publiſhing of Laws be the exerciſe of a regal Power and Authority, there will be more Kings in every Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, than were ever yet called by that name.</p>
            <p>He adds ibid. <hi>That our Saviour tells Pilate he was born to be a King,</hi> quoting <hi>Joh.</hi> 18. <hi>v.</hi> 37. And yet our Saviour neither there, nor any<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where elſe uſeth any words of ſuch an import, either unto <hi>Pilate,</hi> or any one elſe. Chriſt was not born to be a King, but was born a King. I had took no notice of this, but that I ſmelt a Socinian rat in it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 6. <q>That to which we commonly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriate the name of Regal Power, is that Authority which he is inveſted with to govern his Church, to ſend his Spirit to forgive ſins, to diſpenſe his grace and ſupernatural aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, to anſwer Prayers, to raiſe the dead, and judge the world, and beſtow immortal life on all his ſincere Diſciples; all this is the reward of his death, and ſufferings, and is therefore called his Interceſſion, becauſe like the interceſſion of the High-Prieſt, under the Law it is founded on his expiation and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice.</q>
            </p>
            <p>This is a ſtrain of new Divinity, ſo new that perhaps the world never ſaw it in Print, till it was ſo unhappy as to be peſtered with <hi>Socinus.</hi> All the things here ſpoken of do agree to <hi>Christ</hi> as <hi>God-man,</hi> yet ſo that the <hi>Divine Nature</hi> is chiefly to be eyed and to be look'd upon as the <hi>principle</hi> or <hi>fountain,</hi> the <hi>humane Nature</hi> afford<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:56069:5"/> only an <hi>inferiour instrumental concurrence.</hi> But why ſhould it be ſaid that all theſe are the <hi>reward of Christs death and ſufferings?</hi> Had he not the Authority for all from his incarnation? Did he not <hi>raiſe from the dead,</hi> and <hi>forgive ſins,</hi> and <hi>diſpenſe his grace</hi> and <hi>ſupernatural aſſistan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> before he dyed? what one place of Scripture is there that ſayes, <hi>the power of forgiving ſins, or raiſing from the dead was a reward of Christs death and ſufferings?</hi> And where did this Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman learn that all theſe things are call'd <hi>the interceſſion of Christ, and therefore call'd his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſion becauſe founded on his expiation and ſacrifice?</hi> Every thing that is a fruit of <hi>Christs interceſſion</hi> is not preſently in Scripture <hi>called or to be called his interceſſion.</hi> And he writes very looſely and wildly, <hi>pag.</hi> 7. when having quoted <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.12. He adds, <hi>ſo that interceſſion ſignifies the administration of Christs Mediatory Kingdom, the power of a Regal Priest to expiate and forgive ſins.</hi> For neither doth <hi>the interceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Christ</hi> ſo ſignifie, nor if it did ſo ſignifie, could ſuch a ſignification be collected from that place of Scripture where the word <hi>interceſſion</hi> is not uſed, nor any other word equivalent thereunto.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 8. <q>Though Chriſt is originally the name of an Office, yet it is in Scripture uſed to ſignifie the Perſon who is inveſted with this Office.</q>
            </p>
            <p>This is a rare and odd notion, for as the word <hi>Christ</hi> never ſignifies the <hi>Office abstracted from the perſon,</hi> ſo it never ſignifies the <hi>Perſon, but as invested with the Office.</hi> And he that can di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:56069:6"/> this ſecond acceptation of the word from the firſt, and make ſence of both, I think muſt be more ſubtile than <hi>Doctor Subtilis</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. What follows that, <hi>the Lord before his deſignation to the Office was publickly owned, was only call'd Jeſus.</hi> Either I do not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, or elſe it is very falſe, for <hi>when was our Lords deſignation to his Office publickly owned?</hi> A man would think by what is added that this Authour thought it was <hi>not publickly owned,</hi> till he was <hi>rais'd from the dead.</hi> For theſe are his words, <hi>In the Goſpels which contain the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>story of his life and death, he is called Jeſus al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes, becauſe all this time it was diſputed whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he was the Christ or no.</hi> But I am ſure that the Goſpels contain the Hiſtory of his <hi>reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,</hi> as well as of his <hi>life</hi> and <hi>death,</hi> and that he is not <hi>alwayes in the Goſpel called Jeſus,</hi> but he is called <hi>Jeſus Christ</hi> in the very firſt Verſe of St. <hi>Matthew's Gospel,</hi> and that he was called <hi>Christ</hi> as well as <hi>Jeſus</hi> before his reſurrection, not only by his Diſciples, but by ſuch who had not courage or faith enough to become his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples. Had it been otherwiſe, the <hi>Iews</hi> would not have thought it neceſſary to make a Law againſt thoſe who ſaid he was the <hi>Christ.</hi> The reaſon why the <hi>Evangeliſts</hi> uſe the name <hi>Jeſus</hi> more frequently than the name <hi>Chriſt,</hi> could not be becauſe in the life-time of <hi>Chriſt</hi> it was diſputed whether <hi>Jeſus</hi> were the <hi>Chriſt,</hi> for the Goſpels were all written after the <hi>reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of Chriſt,</hi> and one of them was written after all <hi>Paul</hi>'s Epiſtles were written, at which time there were many Churches founded
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:56069:6"/> on this perſwaſion and belief, that <hi>Jeſus</hi> was the <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 9. He acquaints us, <hi>That Chriſt ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſignifies the Goſpel and Religion of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I think in the Sacred Scripture it doth ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſo ſignifie, but wiſh he had not brought <hi>Col.</hi> 2.8. as an inſtance of that ſignification. The <hi>Socinians</hi> would be glad to have it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincingly proved that the word <hi>Chriſt</hi> is there uſed for <hi>Chriſt's Doctrine and Religion,</hi> or <hi>Goſpel,</hi> for ſo they would have it to ſignifie, and thence they infer that the words in the 9th Verſe are not a ſufficient argument to prove <hi>Chriſt's Divinity.</hi> 'Tis, ſay they, not the <hi>humane Nature</hi> of Chriſt, but <hi>the Goſpel of Chriſt,</hi> in which <hi>the fulneſs of the Godhead dwelleth bodily,</hi> and they prove it by ſo expounding the 8th Verſe, as Mr. <hi>Sh.</hi> expounds it.</p>
            <p>I grant alſo that the word <hi>Chriſt,</hi> doth as he notes <hi>pag.</hi> 11. <hi>ſometimes ſignifie the Church of Chriſt which is his body, the fulneſs of him that filleth all in all:</hi> But I deny that we muſt thus underſtand thoſe Phraſes of <hi>being in Chriſt, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grafted into Chriſt, united to Chriſt;</hi> I deny that theſe Phraſes ſignifie no more than to be <hi>one who belongs to the Society whereof Chriſt is the head.</hi> The whole Church is <hi>in Chriſt,</hi> and ſhall we ſay that the Church, being <hi>in Chriſt,</hi> is the Churches being <hi>in it ſelf:</hi> A <hi>particular</hi> Church may be ſaid to be <hi>in God the Father,</hi> as well as in <hi>God the Son;</hi> ſo is the <hi>Church of the Theſſalonians</hi> ſaid to be, 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1.1. Would it be handſome thus to Paraphraſe the Apoſtles words, <hi>unto the Church of the Theſſalonians
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:56069:7"/> which is in God the Father, and the Lord Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> that is, <hi>which is in the Church.</hi> It may be, this Gentleman means that for a <hi>particular believer to be in Chriſt,</hi> is no more than to be <hi>in the Church,</hi> and that in order of Nature, a man is firſt united to the <hi>Church,</hi> then to <hi>Chriſt;</hi> and if this be his meaning, then he muſt hold that the firſt believer, whoever he was, was not <hi>in Chriſt;</hi> until he had a certain num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of fellow-believers, enough to make <hi>a Church,</hi> and then all together were united unto <hi>Chriſt;</hi> and had his firſt fellow-believers fallen off from <hi>Chriſt,</hi> then had he again been not uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted unto <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and muſt have waited till there had been other members making a Church, and by joyning himſelf unto them, then, and not till then had he been again united to <hi>Chriſt.</hi> If this be that which he aims at, he will not ſure expect we ſhould forthwith receive his Doctrine; and he ſhall do well not to make the receiving of this an Article of Church-Communion, leſt he ſhould find it unpoſſible upon theſe terms ever to gather a Church; doubtleſs every one that is ſanctified doth firſt <hi>ſubmit himſelf to Chriſt,</hi> and by <hi>ſubmitting unto Chriſt,</hi> he is in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>Chriſt in him;</hi> but ſuch is his <hi>ſubmiſſion unto Chriſt,</hi> that it inclines him to ſubmit himſelf to the <hi>Miniſters of Chriſt,</hi> and to walk in all or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances with thoſe that have ſubmitted to the Laws and Government of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> as well as himſelf. Indeed the <hi>Church of Chriſt</hi> can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive no Member till there be preſumption that <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath firſt received that Member, and that Member received <hi>Chriſt:</hi> And a man's <hi>union
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:56069:7"/> to Chriſt,</hi> doth in order of Nature precede his <hi>union to the Church,</hi> and would continue, though a man ſhould ſuppoſe (which perhaps is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible) that there ſhould be no Church for him to be united to. And if this Gentleman thinks it unintelligible, How a Believer ſhould be <hi>in Chriſt, and Chriſt in a Believer,</hi> he may be pleaſed to know, that it is unintelligible to none but himſelf.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 22. <q>He hath told us there <hi>(in the Goſpel)</hi> whatever he intends to do for us, and hath charged us to expect no more from him.</q>
            </p>
            <p>If the meaning be that, <hi>Chriſt hath in his Goſpel told us on what terms we muſt expect Juſtification, Adoption, Glorification, and charged us not to expect theſe on lower or eaſier terms than are expreſſed in the Goſpel,</hi> I muſt needs ſay, your <hi>Author</hi> is not miſtaken; but if that be his only meaning, he is not the happieſt man in the world in expreſſing himſelf; for his words ſound as if he were of the mind of the <hi>wildeſt Fanaticks,</hi> who are of Opinion, <hi>That Chriſt in his Goſpel hath told us all the remarkable particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larities of his Providence towards the Church, even till time ſhall be no more. Chriſt hath told us in the Goſpel whatever he intends to do for us.</hi> What can this import leſs, than that <hi>Chriſt hath told us in the Goſpel, that at ſuch a time Kingly and Epiſcopal Government ſhould be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored here in England?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 26. <q>He raiſed up ſome great exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, and Preachers of Righteouſneſs, ſuch as <hi>Enoch,</hi> and <hi>Noah</hi> and <hi>Abraham;</hi> and gave
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:56069:8"/> ſuch plain and undenyable proofs of his ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance of theſe men, as might reaſonably encourage others to imitate their examples. He tranſlated <hi>Enoch</hi> immediately to Heaven, and preſerved <hi>Noah</hi> and his Family in the Ark, when he deſtroyed the reſt of the World by a deluge of Waters, he ſent <hi>Lot</hi> out of the ruines of <hi>Sodom,</hi> and made <hi>Abraham</hi> the Father of a great Nation; which was a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincing Argument how dear theſe good men were to God, and what others might expect from him, who would worſhip and fear him as they did.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Something in theſe words is <hi>queſtionable,</hi> ſomething <hi>falſe.</hi> 1. It is <hi>queſtionable,</hi> whether <hi>God immediately tranſlated Enoch to Heaven;</hi> and therefore it would have become this young Divine, not barely to affirm, but ſtrongly to prove <hi>Enoch</hi>'s <hi>Tranſlation to Heaven;</hi> and when he hath proved that, it will be another work to prove that he was <hi>immediately tranſlated to Heaven.</hi> 2. It is <hi>falſe,</hi> that the Favours of God to <hi>Enoch, Noah, Lot, Abraham, are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincing Arguments what others may expect from him, who will worſhip and fear him as they did.</hi> Hundreds and thouſands have <hi>worſhipped and feared God as they did,</hi> who never expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from him ſuch extraordinary Favours and Rarities of Grace as thoſe Elders had vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafed to them, nor indeed had they any ground to build ſuch an Expection on.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 27. <q>When God choſe the Poſterity of <hi>Abraham</hi> to be his peculiar People, he did not deſign to exclude the reſt of the World
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:56069:8"/> from his Care and Providence, and all poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Means of Salvation, as the Apoſtle ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues in <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.29. <hi>Is be the God of the Jews onely? is he not alſo of the Gentiles? yes, of the Gentiles alſo:</hi> which Argument if it have any force in it, muſt prove Gods reſpect to the Gentiles before the Preaching of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, as well as ſince, becauſe it is founded on that natural Relation God owns to all Mankind, as their merciful Creator, and Governour; which gives the Gentiles as well as the Jewes, an intereſt in his Care and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence.</q>
            </p>
            <p>True it is, that <hi>Gods chooſing the ſeed of Abraham, did not exclude all the reſt of the World from his Care and Providence, nor make ſalvation impoſſible to the reſt of Mankind.</hi> But when God <hi>choſe Iſrael,</hi> he did for many years <hi>reject the reſt of the World from his ſpecial care and Providence,</hi> and from all <hi>ordinary</hi> wayes and means of Salvation. If God ſaved any but the <hi>Jews,</hi> it was by bringing them among the <hi>Jews,</hi> or the <hi>Jews</hi> among them; or by ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainting them in ſome extraordinary way with the ſubſtance of that Doctrine concerning the <hi>promiſed ſeed</hi> that was ordinarily preached a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the <hi>Jews.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 29 <q>He <hi>(God)</hi> committed his Laws and Oracles to them <hi>(the People of Iſrael)</hi> from whence the reſt of the world, when they pleaſed, might fetch the beſt Rules of Life, and the moſt certain notices of the Divine Will.</q>
            </p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:56069:9"/>
            <p>This is very ſtrange, and next to impoſſible; the reſt of the world could not <hi>fetch the Laws from the People of Iſrael,</hi> unleſs they knew that there were ſuch a People as the people of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and that they had the <hi>Oracles of God</hi> among them, and which was the way to travel to this people. And did the one half of the world know this? But let us ſuppoſe that all the world knew of the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> and of their <hi>Laws,</hi> and how they might come to the <hi>Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites;</hi> ſuppoſe we alſo that the <hi>Jews</hi> would be ſo kind as to let remote Nations have a ſight and Copy of their Lawes, theſe Laws could be no Notices of the Divine Will, till tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into a known tongue. Were there alwayes among the <hi>Jews</hi> men that could tranſlate the Law into all Languages?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 33. <q>Whereas God was formerly known by the Light of Nature, and the works of Creation and Providence, and thoſe par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial and occaſional Revelations of his Will, which he made to the World; now the onely true <hi>Medium</hi> of knowing God, is the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Chriſt, who came into the World to declare God to us.</q>
            </p>
            <p>If this be not down-right <hi>Fanaticiſm,</hi> I know not what is. Heretofore the <hi>Light of Nature,</hi> and the <hi>Works of Creation and Providence</hi> were true <hi>Mediums</hi> for the knowing of God, now they are not only dark and inſufficient (as they ever were ſince the Fall) but alſo falſe <hi>Mediums</hi> of knowing God. <hi>Chriſt</hi> is the only true <hi>Medium,</hi> all others muſt be thrown away, or not made uſe of, unleſs we deſign to be deceived
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:56069:9"/> by them. Would Mr. <hi>Tho. Brooks</hi> have writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten thus?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 42. <q>The Light of Nature, and the works of Creation and Providence, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures us, that God is ſo good that he deſires and deſigns the happineſs of all his Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures according to the capacity of their Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> very patient and long-ſuffering towards the worſt of men.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Doth not onely the <hi>Revelation made by Chriſt,</hi> but alſo the <hi>Light of Nature</hi> aſſure us, that <hi>God deſires and deſigns the happineſs of all his Creatures according to the capacity of their Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures?</hi> How then comes it to paſs, that all his creatures are not happy? doth God fail of his <hi>deſire?</hi> doth he miſcarry in his <hi>deſign?</hi> or do the creatures loſe the <hi>capacity of their Natures?</hi> As for <hi>patience</hi> and <hi>long-ſufferance</hi> God exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed none towards the fallen <hi>Angels,</hi> nor do we find that <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi> after their Fall had any expectation that God would exerciſe it towards them. Indeed the Hiſtories of <hi>God's</hi> Providence manifeſt that he hath very long en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured ſome very bad men (which was a great ſtone of offence to ſome of the greateſt <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers</hi>) with others not ſo bad, as far as we could judge, he made <hi>ſhort work in righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs;</hi> ſo that ſinners have little reaſon to promiſe themſelves that God will ſpare them, when they wilfully ſin againſt him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 44. <q>It is not poſſible to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand what Goodneſs is, without pardoning Grace.</q>
            </p>
            <p>A very bold and rude Aſſertion. <hi>God</hi> is good
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:56069:10"/> to all his Creatures, and yet ſome of them need no <hi>pardoning Grace,</hi> becauſe they never ſinned; others of his creatures cannot ſin, becauſe they have no notions of <hi>God,</hi> nor of a <hi>Law,</hi> and ſo they are uncapable of <hi>pardoning Grace.</hi> Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps this Author would be underſtood of <hi>ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full</hi> creatures, they may be aſſured that <hi>God</hi> is <hi>very good,</hi> and good he cannot be without par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doning Grace. If ſo, let <hi>God</hi> look to it; <hi>Maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus</hi> he may be accounted, but <hi>Optimus</hi> he may not look to be called, if he do not find out ſome way to pardon ſin, and make ſome diſcovery to all ſinners, that he is ready to pardon them, till he hath done this, they <hi>cannot underſtand that he is good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 45. <q>That God is ſo Juſt and Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, that he cannot pardon ſin without ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction to his Juſtice, is ſuch a Notion of Juſtice that is perfectly new, which neither Scripture, nor Nature aquaints us with.</q>
            </p>
            <p>That <hi>God cannot forgive ſin without ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> I did never yet believe, nor ſhall as I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe ever be brought to believe. Yet I ſhould account I had made ſhipwrack of all Modeſty, if I ſhould be ſo hardy as to affirm this Notion, That Gods Juſtice cannot be diverted from ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners without the interpoſing of a Propitiation, is <hi>perfectly new.</hi> Many well acquainted with <hi>Nature</hi> and <hi>Scripture,</hi> did in former Ages be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, as alſo in this preſent Age many do ſtill believe, it implyes a contradiction, that the rational creature made under a Law with a a ſanction, and having broken that Law, ſhould not either be puniſhed in his own perſon, or in
<pb facs="tcp:56069:10"/> ſome one that undertook for him. Yea, there be ſome of greater Learning than I can hope to attain to, who ſay, that <hi>pardon of ſin with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſatisfaction is ſimply impoſſible, though it had never been ſaid to Adam, In the day thou eateſt thereof, thou ſhalt die the death: Quia im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicit ut Deus habeat ſupremum &amp; abſolutum Dominium in hominem, &amp; homo non obligetur ad actualem obedientiam, aut eâ deficiente ad vicariam ejus compenſationem per poenam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And I muſt needs ſay, that the learned are confirmed in theſe Opinions, by the weak Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions that ſome men make againſt them, and that one can ſcarce imagine a weaker Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to be made, than what is made by this <hi>Predicant, pag.</hi> 48.</p>
            <p>
               <q>If Juſtice be ſo natural to God, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing could ſatisfie him but the Death of his Son, the Redemption of the World by Chriſt may diſcover his Juſtice or his Goodneſs, but not his Wiſdom; for Wiſdom conſiſts in the choice of the beſt and fitteſt Means to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain an End, when there are more wayes of doing it.</q>
            </p>
            <p>If there be any <hi>wit</hi> in this Argument, ſurely there is not much <hi>wiſdom</hi> nor <hi>judgement</hi> in it; for <hi>wiſdom</hi> may very well conſiſt in finding out <hi>fit</hi> means that are not very obvious for attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an End, though there be <hi>no other</hi> means for the attaining of that End. Let Mr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> find out the <hi>Quadrature of a Circle,</hi> and we will count him a <hi>wiſe man,</hi> and never put him to the trouble of demonſtrating that there were other wayes of finding out that <hi>Knack,</hi> only
<pb facs="tcp:56069:11"/> his way was the <hi>fitteſt</hi> and <hi>beſt:</hi> Yea, let him but find out a ſatisfactory <hi>medium</hi> to prove that the <hi>Faculties</hi> are <hi>really diſtinct,</hi> or are <hi>not really diſtinct</hi> in the Soul, and we will crie him up for a <hi>wiſe man,</hi> and never enquire whether there were not other <hi>mediums</hi> to prove thoſe Concluſions by. But the truth is, this <hi>pert Preacher</hi> underſtands not the Queſtion betwixt himſelf and Dr. <hi>J. O.</hi> as will appear from what he layes down <hi>pag.</hi> 50. <q>The Deſert of ſin is ſuch, that it is impoſſible to make any ſatisfaction to the Juſtice of God, but onely by the death of Chriſt, otherwiſe Chriſt had died in vain.</q> This one would think ſhould go down without much chewing, and ſo indeed it would, but that Mr. <hi>S.</hi> could not or would not underſtand the meaning of it, for thus he explains it, <q>That is, that God could not forgive it <hi>(ſin)</hi> without full ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, which nothing but the Death of Chriſt could make.</q> I appeal to all men of common ſence and reaſon, whether theſe two Propoſitions be the ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <q>It is impoſſible to make ſatisfaction to the Juſtice of God but by the Death of Chriſt; God cannot forgive ſin without full ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 52. <q>Vindictive Juſtice and pardoning Mercy are but ſecondary Attributes of the Divine Nature.</q>
            </p>
            <p>This ſeems to me a ſpick and ſpan new Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, and I hope it never before this time dropped from any mans pen. Very abſurd I am ſure it is.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:56069:11"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 58. <q>By this it appears how rigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly juſt God is, that he will never par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don the leaſt ſin, when he can ſerve his own Glory by the miſery and confuſion of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By this;</hi> by what? if he can frame any Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions or Premiſes of Dr. <hi>Owen,</hi> from which ſo abſurd a concluſion can be drawn, then ſhall I wiſh that ſuch a creature as Dr. <hi>Owen</hi> had never been born; let him when he next puts out, try his skill in <hi>Logick.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I am almoſt weary of raking in a Dunghill, and therefore you muſt excuſe me, if I take no notice of any thing elſe till I come to <hi>pag.</hi> 107. where thus our Author phraſifyeth, <q>If we would get the Bleſſing, we muſt go to God, as <hi>Jacob</hi> did, in the Robes of our Elder Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, though I confeſs this reſemblance doth not pleaſe me very well; for though <hi>Jacob</hi> was a good man, yet this looks like a cunning trick, to rob his elder Brother of the Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, and to cheat his blind Father; and men muſt not think that God is thus to be impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed on.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Who they be that have made uſe of this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblance, he diſcovereth not; yet it is like enough ſome <hi>Non-conforming Divines</hi> may be intended; nor can I deny that ſome of them have made uſe of it, ſundry of the <hi>ancient Fathers</hi> had ſo done before they were born. This Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor ſaith, <hi>it pleaſeth him not very well;</hi> if it do not, let all the <hi>Non-conforming Miniſters</hi> have a care that they mention it no more, for Mr. <hi>Sh.</hi> is one that if he be not <hi>very well pleaſed,</hi> will
<pb facs="tcp:56069:12"/> lay about him, and make the whole Nation witneſſes of his diſpleaſure. But, as I ſaid before, the <hi>Fathers</hi> made uſe of this reſemblance before the <hi>Non-conformiſts</hi> medled with it, and is it come to that paſs, that a <hi>poor Predicant</hi> muſt be jeered for ſpeaking as the Fathers did? Time was I am certain, when a <hi>Miniſter</hi> that was called in queſtion for a <hi>Puritanical</hi> Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, came off well enough when he made it appear, that the moſt offenſive paſſages were but St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> tranſlated. This notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, I am not huge fond of the <hi>Reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance,</hi> and ſhall be content it be laid aſide, if Mr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> can but prevail to have another Reſemblance laid aſide, which I think I have as little reaſon to be <hi>well pleaſed</hi> with: A certain <hi>conforming Miniſter</hi> was wont alway to have this in his form of Prayer before Sermon, <hi>Grant that with the good Thief on the Croſs we may ſteal Heaven when we die.</hi> By a little enquiry he may find out the man, and if he can prevail with him to omit it, I will uſe my intereſt with any Non-conformiſt I am acquainted with, no more to uſe the <hi>Reſemblance of Jacobs putting on the Garments of his elder Brother, and in them getting the Bleſſing.</hi> Yet I aſſure him, I heard it very largely inſiſted on, in a Sermon made by one of the preſent <hi>Prebends</hi> of <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 119. Mr. <hi>Sh.</hi> falls upon thoſe who ſay that <q>Faith juſtifieth as it brings us to Chriſt, and makes us one with him by whom we are juſtified; Faith apprehends the the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of Chriſt, and the Righteouſneſs of
<pb facs="tcp:56069:12"/> Chriſt juſtifieth.</q> 
               <hi>Well what hath he againſt this Diſtinction? he ſaith,</hi> 
               <q>It plainly oweth it ſelf to their preconceived Opinions, without which no man could ever have ſtumbled on't. That when the Scripture ſaith, that Faith juſtifieth, the meaning ſhould be, that it juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies and ſaves inſtrumentally and relatively, <hi>(words which the Scriptures are unacquainted with)</hi> i. e. not as it is Faith, but as it appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hends the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt, which in plain words ſignifieth, that Faith doth not juſtifie, though the Scripture ſo often ſayes it does.</q>
            </p>
            <p>If this Gentleman think Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> hath not ſufficiently beaten thoſe who thus miſre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent <hi>Faith's concurrence to Juſtification,</hi> good leave he hath from me to take his Cudgel and to bang them: But let him not lay about him without fear or wit, as here he ſeems to do. They will but laugh at him, if he tell them, <hi>That the Scripture often ſayes, that Faith juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies;</hi> for they have been told, That <hi>Scripture no where ſaith Faith juſtifieth,</hi> though it often ſpeak of <hi>being juſtified by Faith.</hi> Hath this Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine ſo much forgot his <hi>Grammar,</hi> as to know no diſtinction betwixt <hi>justifieth</hi> and <hi>being juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied?</hi> And can he imagine that the world will believe his Adverſaries to be ſo ſimple, as to ſay, that the meaning of <hi>Faith's juſtifying</hi> is, that it <hi>juſtifieth</hi> and <hi>ſaveth too?</hi> But I were beſt beware how I meddle with this <hi>great Author,</hi> who ſpeaks of himſelf as if he had read all that ever did write, and had heard all that ever did ſpeak.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:56069:13"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 121. He blames Mr. <hi>Watſon,</hi> for ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>All that Faith doth is to bring home Chriſts merits to the ſoul,</hi> adding, <q>If you can but find out an improper and abſurd form of ſpeech in uſe among the Vulgar, or if you can but invent one, as this Gentleman doth, for I never met with this before, it is a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient reaſon to expound Scripture as im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>properly as unlearned men talk or think.</q>
            </p>
            <p>If his <hi>for</hi> have any <hi>reaſon</hi> in it, and certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he intended it ſhould have ſome, then it is thus to be formed, <hi>That which Mr.</hi> Watſon <hi>uſeth, and I never met with before, that Mr.</hi> Watſon <hi>invented: This phraſe Mr.</hi> Watſon <hi>uſeth, and I never met with it before, therefore he invented it.</hi> Juſt at the ſame rate he muſt be conceived to argue, <hi>pag.</hi> 128. <hi>That which I never read of before, is a very new conceit: I never read before of Faith's ſucking Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion out of the ſpiritual Stomack; therefore it is a very new conceit.</hi> This is juſt according to the old Obſervation, that <hi>Young men are confident.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir, I am not now Apologizing for Mr. <hi>Wat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> he is of Age, and can ſpeak for himſelf, if he count it needfull; nor have I Mr. <hi>Watſons</hi> Books by me; if I had, perhaps I might find that he is abuſed, for I do aſſure you, Mr <hi>Sh.</hi> doth not much ſtick at abuſing and wronging thoſe whom he deals with: ſo that when an <hi>ordinary Reader</hi> would ſuppoſe he beats his Adverſaries, a <hi>Scholar</hi> may ſoon find he one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly threſheth a man of Clouts of his own make<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:56069:13"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 132. He takes Dr. <hi>O.</hi> as I ſuppoſe to task for ſaying, <q>That though Holineſs be nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the cauſe, matter, nor condition of Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication; yet it is the way appointed by God for us to walk in, for the obtaining Salvation.</q> Now what hath he againſt this? he confeſſeth it is, <q>home to the purpoſe, but yet there are two little faults in it, that it contradicts it ſelf, and overthrows their darling opinion; which I can very well pardon, if he can.</q> Really he is a good natured man that can ſo very well pardon a contradiction, he had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicted himſelf, as I noted before, and needing pardon from others, will give pardon to others; but I pray you what contradiction is there in the Dr's words? why this is a contradiction, that Holineſs ſhould be affirmed to be the <hi>neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary way to eternal life;</hi> and yet neither the <hi>cauſe, matter,</hi> nor <hi>condition:</hi> this looks I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs like a contradiction, but now the Dr. did not ſay, <hi>That Holineſs was neither the cauſe, matter, nor condition of eternal life or ſalvation, but neither the cauſe, matter, nor condition of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification;</hi> let us ſet Dr. <hi>Owen</hi>'s two Propoſitions together: <hi>Holineſs is neither the cauſe, matter, nor condition of our Juſtification. Holineſs it the way appointed by God for us to walk in, for the obtaining of Salvation.</hi> What <hi>contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction</hi> is there in theſe two <hi>Propoſitions?</hi> juſt as much as there is betwixt two <hi>Propoſitions</hi> that conſiſt not of the ſame <hi>predicate;</hi> that is, none at all. Mr. <hi>Sh.</hi> may do well to ſtudy his <hi>Logick</hi> again, and find out there what a <hi>contradiction</hi> is, before he charge any <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:56069:14"/> 
               <hi>Dr. of Divinity</hi> with a <hi>Contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 137. Mr. <hi>Sh.</hi> falls into a fit of Admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>at the Wiſdom and honeſty of our Church of</hi> England, <hi>who in her publick Catechiſm</hi> (he takes no notice of her Articles or her Homilies) <hi>hath been careful to prevent cheats and deluſions of fancy, feeds her Children with wholeſom and ſubſtantial food, hath taught them a Religion without art or ſubtlety, hath inſtructed them in the Nature of their Baptiſmal vow, and thoſe Obligations it layes on them to a vertuous life: hath taught them the Apoſtles Creed, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains thoſe great and eſſential Articles of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, which are the neceſſary principles of Action,</hi> (i. e. hath taught them to ſay them, but hath not explained the one half of them) <hi>hath given them a plain and eaſie explication of the Ten Commandments, which are the rules of good life, hath taught them to pray to God,</hi> (by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounding to be learn'd the Lord's prayer with out the Doxology) <hi>and what the true deſign of our Saviours Inſtitutions is, without filling their heads with Notions and Artificial Theories of Religion, which ſerve only to make them giddy with a vain conceit of knowledge, to talk ill and to live worſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have already noted by the by, that the Gentleman takes no notice of the <hi>Churches</hi> ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Articles</hi> or <hi>Homilies,</hi> had he touched them he would have found himſelf to have a <hi>wolf by the Ears.</hi> For though perhaps he laughs at the <hi>Articles</hi> and <hi>Homilies</hi> in his ſleeve, yet he hath more either of wiſdom or honeſty,
<pb facs="tcp:56069:14"/> than openly to gibe at them, to which he hath ſubſcribed; and yet if he had recited their words, the world would ſoon have ſeen that the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons formed againſt Dr. <hi>O.</hi> Mr. <hi>W.</hi> might have been uſed as ſucceſsfully againſt the contrivers of our <hi>Articles</hi> and <hi>Homilies,</hi> and the Authors of other writings allowed by <hi>Royal Authority.</hi> In King <hi>Edward</hi>'s dayes, Biſhop <hi>Poinet</hi>'s <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſm</hi> was appointed to be taught in Schools, Mr. <hi>Nowel</hi>'s <hi>Catechiſm</hi> was authorized in Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s dayes, and I think ſtill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinueth to be the <hi>authorized Catechiſm;</hi> in thoſe <hi>Catechiſms</hi> I find faith called <hi>the hand, and the mouth,</hi> and yet this <hi>man of Drollery</hi> thinks, that if <hi>faith were not a very humble grace, ſhe would never take ſuch language.</hi> But I will not hope to repreſs the <hi>petulance</hi> of his wit, by the <hi>Authority</hi> of theſe <hi>Catechiſms,</hi> he will ſay they are deſigned for <hi>School-boyes,</hi> and not for <hi>Divines,</hi> the <hi>Homilies</hi> ſhould be read by him on <hi>Holy-dayes,</hi> unleſs he have then a <hi>Sermon,</hi> and he hath acknowledged them to <hi>contain a good and wholſome Doctrine,</hi> let us try whether they do not lye as open to this Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man's <hi>Witticiſms,</hi> as the <hi>Sermons</hi> or <hi>Diſcourſes</hi> of <hi>J. O.</hi> and <hi>T. W.</hi> The Sermons in the firſt <hi>Tome of Homilies</hi> that treat of <hi>Juſtification,</hi> are entituled <hi>of Salvation.</hi> Thus begins the firſt; <q>Becauſe all men be ſinners, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> therefore can no man by his own acts, works, deeds, (ſeem they never ſo good) be juſtified and made righteous before God; but every man is conſtrained of neceſſity to ſeek for another righteouſneſs or juſtification to be received at
<pb facs="tcp:56069:15"/> God's own hands, <hi>i. e.</hi> the forgiveneſs of ſins. And this juſtification or righteouſneſs, which we ſo receive of God's mercies, and Chriſt's merits, embraced by faith, is taken, accepted, allowed of God for our perfect and full juſtification.</q>
            </p>
            <p>I was about to tranſcribe much of the <hi>Homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies,</hi> but ſeeing they are in many mens hands, and ſhould be in all Churches, that will be need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, therefore I ſhall only excerpe ſome Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions out of them, and quote the pages according to the Edition by <hi>John Bill,</hi> 1623.</p>
            <p>
               <q>All the world being wrapped in ſin, God ſent his only Son our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt into this world to fulfil the Law for us, <hi>&amp;c. p.</hi> 13.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>God provided a Ranſome for us, the moſt precious blood of his own moſt dear, and beſt beloved Son Jeſus Chriſt, who beſides this Ranſome, fulfilled the Law for us per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly, <hi>pag.</hi> 14.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>St. <hi>Paul</hi> declareth nothing upon the behalf of man concerning his Juſtification, but only a true and lively Faith, which nevertheleſs is the gift of God, and not man's only work without God, and yet that faith doth not ſhut out Repentance, Hope, Love, Dread, and the fear of God, to be joyned with faith in every man that is Juſtified; but it ſhutteth them out from the Office or Juſtifying. So that although they be all preſent together in him that is juſtified, yet they juſtifie not alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. Nor the faith alſo doth not ſhut out
<pb facs="tcp:56069:15"/> the Juſtice of our good works neceſſary to be done afterwards of duty towards God, but it excludeth them, ſo that we may not do them to this intent to be made good by doing of them, <hi>pag.</hi> 14, 15.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>Chriſt is now the Righteouſneſs of all them that truly do believe in him; he for them paid their Ranſome by his Death: He for them fulfilled the Law in his life, <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>Juſtification is not the office of Man, but of God; or Man cannot make himſelf righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous by his own works, neither in part, nor in the whole, for that were the greateſt arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancy and preſumption of man, that Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt could ſet up againſt God, to affirm that a man may by his own works take away and purge his own Sins, &amp; ſo juſtifie himſelf, <hi>p.</hi> 17.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>The true underſtanding of this Doctrine, <hi>we be juſtified freely by faith without works;</hi> is not, that this our own act, to believe in Chriſt, or this our faith in Chriſt which is within us, doth juſtifie, and deſerve our Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication unto us (for that were to count our ſelves to be juſtified by ſome act or vertue that is within our ſelves) but, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Ibid.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>Faith in Chriſt (as it were) ſaith unto us thus, it is not I that take away your ſins, but it is Chriſt only, and to him only I ſend you for that purpoſe, forſaking therein all your good vertues, words, thoughts, and works, and only putting your truſt in Chriſt, <hi>p.</hi> 18.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>Becauſe faith doth directly ſend us to Chriſt for remiſſion of our ſins, and that by faith gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven us of God, we embrace the promiſe of
<pb facs="tcp:56069:16"/> God's mercy, and of the remiſſion of our ſins (which thing none other of our vertues or works properly doth) therefore Scripture uſeth to ſay, that faith without works doth juſtifie, <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>All the Fathers, Martyrs, and other Holy men (whom St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpake of <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.) had their faith ſurely fixed in God when all the world was againſt them. They did not only know God to be the Lord, Maker and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour of all men in the world, but alſo they had a ſpecial confidence and truſt, that he was, and would be their God, their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forter, aider, helper, maintainer, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender. This is the Chriſtian faith which theſe Holy men had, and we alſo ought to have. And although they were not named Chriſtian-men, yet it was a Chriſtian-faith that they had, for they looked for all benefits of God the Father, through the merits of his Son Jeſus Chriſt, as we now do. This diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence is between them and us, that they looked when Chriſt ſhould come, and we be in the time when he is come. Therefore ſaith St. <hi>Aug.</hi> the time is altered and changed, but not the faith; for we have both one faith in one Chriſt. The ſame Holy Ghoſt alſo which we have, had they. God gave them then Grace to be his Children, as he doth us now, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> In effect they and we be all one, we have the ſame faith they had in God, and they the ſame we have, <hi>pag.</hi> 25.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>Faith giveth life to the Soul, and they be as much dead to God that lack faith, as they be
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:56069:16"/> to the world, whoſe bodies lack ſouls; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out faith all that is done of us, is but dead before God, although the work ſeem never ſo gay and glorious before man. Even as the picture graven or painted, is but a dead re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentation of the thing it ſelf, and is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out life, or any manner of moving; ſo be the works of all unfaithful perſons before God. They do appear to be lively works, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed they be but dead, not availing to the everlaſting life. They be but ſhadows &amp; ſhews of lively and good things, and not good and lively things indeed. For true faith doth give life to the works, and out of ſuch faith come good works, that be very good works indeed, &amp; without faith, no work is good before God, as ſaith St. <hi>Aug. pag.</hi> 30. And there, and in <hi>pag.</hi> 31, 32. much is quoted to the ſame purpoſe out of St. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> St. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> St. <hi>Chryſoſtom.</hi> Among other things, this is quoted with approbation from <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> I can ſhew a man that by faith without works, lived and came to Heaven; but without faith never man had life. The Thief that was hanged, when Chriſt ſuffered, did believe only, and the moſt mereiful God juſtified him. And becauſe no man ſhall ſay again that he lacked time to do good works, elſe he would have done them: Truth it is, and I will not contend therein, but this I will ſurely affirm, that faith only ſaved him. If he had lived, and not regarded faith, and the works thereof, he ſhould have loſt his ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion again. But this is the effect that I ſay,
<pb facs="tcp:56069:17"/> that faith by it ſelf ſaved him, but works by themſelves never juſtified any man.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe are ſome of many things which I could have quoted out of the <hi>Homilies,</hi> which Mr. <hi>Sh.</hi> is bound to read to his people, and which were publiſhed by Queen <hi>Elizabeth, to expel erroneous and poyſonous Doctrine,</hi> and were reprinted by King <hi>James,</hi> not only for <hi>a help of Non-Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching,</hi> but withall, as a <hi>pattern for Preaching Miniſters.</hi> How ill Mr. <hi>Sh.</hi> hath fitted his cloath to this pattern, he that is not very blind may ſee; ſomebody perhaps may be at ſo much trouble, as to gather up his <hi>drolling Parentheſis,</hi> and adapt them to the expreſſions in the <hi>Homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies,</hi> compoſed perhaps, as to the firſt Tome of them by Arch. <hi>Cranmer,</hi> and as to the laſt of them by a <hi>Prelate</hi> not inferior to him for learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and piety. I have no mind to make the <hi>Papiſts</hi> and other <hi>Sectaries</hi> ſo much ſport. But certainly had I a Cure of Souls, I would every <hi>Holy-day</hi> when there was no Sermon in my <hi>Church,</hi> either read or cauſe to be read one of them to my People, and ſhould not dare to expoſe the Doctrines contained in them, as Mr. <hi>Sh.</hi> manifeſtly doth: I might look before I leapt, well conſider whether it were meet to <hi>tye up my ſelf not to contradict ſome paſſages in the</hi> Homilies; but when I had ſo <hi>tyed my ſelf,</hi> I would either ſtrictly obſerve my Obligation, or openly declare my ſorrow for bringing my ſelf under it.</p>
            <p>But becauſe he hath ſo much applauded the <hi>Milk for Babes,</hi> or <hi>the Liturgical Catechiſm,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:56069:17"/> let us take ſome notice of that which for my part I ſo much approve, that I would not for all the Money in my Pocket a new <hi>Catechiſm</hi> were now to be made. In that <hi>Catechiſm</hi> we ſhall find ſomething of <hi>Art and Subtlety</hi> as this Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman would call it. The Child in that <hi>Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſm,</hi> is firſt asked, <hi>What is his Name?</hi> that Queſtion may be anſwered without <hi>Art</hi> or <hi>Subtlety;</hi> but then in the next place, being asked, <hi>who gave him that Name?</hi> he is directed to make anſwer, <hi>My Godfathers, and my Godmothers in my Baptiſm, when I was made a Member of Chriſt, a Child of God,</hi> &amp;c. If the Child was at <hi>Baptiſm made a Member of Chriſt,</hi> he was alſo then <hi>united to Chriſt,</hi> and put <hi>into Chriſt;</hi> for nothing can be a <hi>member of that</hi> unto which it is <hi>not united.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now ſuppoſe any Child ſhould be ſo pert or malepert, as to ask the <hi>Rector</hi> what the word <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſignifieth, when it is ſaid that he was made a <hi>Member of Chriſt;</hi> the <hi>Rector</hi> will gravely anſwer, <hi>Chriſt hath four ſignifications; It ſignifies the Office of Chriſt, the Perſon of Chriſt, the Doctrine of Chriſt, the Church of Chriſt.</hi> The Child was not I ſuppoſe made a <hi>Member of Chriſt's Office,</hi> nor of <hi>Chriſt's Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine;</hi> he muſt be made a <hi>Member</hi> therefore, <hi>either of the Perſon of Chriſt,</hi> or of the <hi>Church of Chriſt.</hi> It is like Mr. <hi>Sh.</hi> will anſwer the Child that he was <hi>made a Member of the Church of Chriſt.</hi> But what this <hi>Church of Chriſt</hi> is, the Child no where finds explained in the <hi>Church Catechiſm.</hi> The <hi>Holy Catholick Church</hi> is mentioned as one of the things to be believed
<pb facs="tcp:56069:18"/> in the <hi>Creed,</hi> and I think the word alſo occurs in the firſt queſtion concerning the <hi>Sacraments,</hi> (which part of the Catechiſm is no older than the <hi>Hampton</hi>-Court Conference) but what the word <hi>Church</hi> ſignifieth is no where opened in that <hi>Catechiſm;</hi> will Mr. <hi>Sh.</hi> now ſay that the Child is to profeſs himſelf a Member of he knows not what? I ſuppoſe he will not, but rather will tell him what the <hi>Church</hi> is, and then he muſt uſe ſome <hi>Art</hi> or <hi>Subtlety</hi> to make him underſtand how he is Member of that <hi>Church;</hi> and I think he muſt be very ſubtle that can make a Child underſtand how he can be a <hi>Member of the Church of Chriſt,</hi> before he have firſt made him underſtand how he was made a <hi>Member of Chriſt himſelf.</hi> And I doubt the Child's head muſt be filled with notions before he can be made underſtand how he is one of thoſe <hi>elect people of God, whom the Spirit ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifieth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You will hope that in the next place I will take Mr. <hi>Sh.</hi> to task for his Expoſition of <hi>John</hi> 15. <hi>v.</hi> 1. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> beginning <hi>p.</hi> 145. but it is ſo Singular, ſo uncouth, ſo forced, that it cannot deſerve conſideration. Our Saviour ſaith, <hi>I am the true Vine, and my Father is the Husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man;</hi> ſome Copies add, <hi>and ye are the Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches.</hi> The meaning, ſaith this grand Interpreter is, <hi>That Church which is founded on the belief of my Goſpel is the true Vine,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. But leſt it ſhould ſeem ſtrange, that Chriſt uſing the firſt perſon ſingular, ſhould mean the Church, he preſently adds, <hi>I, ſignifies Chriſt, together with his Church.</hi> Did ever man write at this
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:56069:18"/> rate? in one humour he ſaith, <hi>I am,</hi> meaneth <hi>the Church is;</hi> within two lines he is in another humour, and then the meaning is, <hi>I am,</hi> i. e. <hi>I and the Church are.</hi> Take him in which hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour you will, neither is very good. <hi>Church</hi> founded on the belief of the Goſpel, there was none when <hi>Chriſt</hi> uſed theſe words; the <hi>Jewiſh Church, State, and Ordinances</hi> then ſtood, and were to ſtand till <hi>Chriſt</hi> dyed. <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelf ſpeaks indeed once of his <hi>Church,</hi> but he ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth of it, not as exiſting, but as that which was to exiſt, not as built, but as to be built: The firſt time we read of any Goſpel Church as exiſting, is in the <hi>Acts.</hi> So then if Mr. <hi>Sh</hi>'s. fancy hold, at this rate our <hi>Bleſſed Saviour</hi> muſt be ſuppoſed to ſpeak, <q>I, and the Goſpel Church which ſhall ſhortly be planted, and the planting whereof I muſt commit to you, are the true Vine, and my Father is the Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandman, and you your ſelves are the bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of this Vine; that is, of me, and of that Church which is made up of you, or muſt be added to you.</q> There's certainly more of <hi>Art</hi> and <hi>Subtlety</hi> than uſually hath been obſerved in any ſpeech of our Saviour that he uſed ſo near his death. But this Gentleman hath four Reaſons to confirm his interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but which of his interpretations I cannot yet tell; only I ſuppoſe he means the laſt. <hi>I, that is, I and my Church,</hi> but let him be thought alſo if you pleaſe, to mean thus, <hi>I, that is, the Church founded on the belief of my Goſpel.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:56069:19"/>
            <p>His firſt reaſon is, becauſe the <q>
                  <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Church is frequently in the Old Teſtament compared to a Vine; now a Vine being the Metaphor whereby the Church uſeth to be deſcribed, we cannot reaſonably underſtand it otherwiſe here.</q>
            </p>
            <p>He ſhould have produced ſome place of the <hi>Old Teſtament,</hi> wherein <hi>God</hi> ſpeaking in the firſt Perſon, called <hi>himſelf and the Jewiſh Church the Vine:</hi> This he doth not, and yet thinks his expoſition cannot reaſonably be refuſed; but I ſuppoſe he will meet with but few that will account themſelves every a whit the more un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable, for refuſing this expoſition con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by no better an argument.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>God</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>is called the Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandman who takes care to dreſs this Vine, which cannot be underſtood of Chriſt, but of the Church.</hi> But by his leave, <hi>God</hi> is not here ſaid to be Husbandman <hi>taking care of the Vine,</hi> but only the Husbandman <hi>pruning, or purging the fruitful branches, and taking away the fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs branches.</hi> Now the branches are Chriſt's Diſciples.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>Chriſt,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>ſpeaks of ſuch branches in him as bear no fruit.</hi> This is boldly ſaid, and cannot be proved if any one will deny it, the words may be read, <hi>not every branch in me that beareth not fruit,</hi> but <hi>every branch that beareth not fruit in me;</hi> ſo the Old <hi>Engliſh Tranſlation</hi> read: ſo the <hi>Syriack</hi> ſeems to have read, ſo <hi>Abbot</hi> againſt <hi>Biſhop</hi> thinks it ſhould be read. But let us not put the Gentleman too hard to it, let us grant that reading which
<pb facs="tcp:56069:19"/> alone can ſerve his turn; what follows? why this, <hi>there can be no branches in the Perſon of Chriſt, not bearing fruit,</hi> Ergo, by <hi>being in him can ſignifie no more than being Members of his viſible Church.</hi> How long ſhall we be wearied with ſuch trifles? there may be <hi>bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches in Chriſt</hi> who do not bear fruit, and all <hi>branches</hi> are ſuch, who be not <hi>in Chriſt</hi> by faith unfeigned, and love undiſſembled.</p>
            <p>In the fourth place he thinks to ſtrike all dead, and to prevent all objections from the Chapter it ſelf, <hi>whence it is evident that when Chriſt ſpeaks in the firſt Perſon, I and mine, he cannot mean this of his own Perſon, but of his Church, Doctrine, and Religion, according as the circumſtances of the place require.</hi> Thus <hi>ver.</hi> 5. <hi>I am the true Vine, ye are the branches; he that abideth in me, and</hi> I <hi>in him, the ſame bringeth forth much fruit, for without me ye can de no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. He would willingly learn what ſenſe can be made of this, if we underſtand it of the Perſon of Chriſt.</hi> If he would willingly learn this, verily he may have many Maſters that will teach him. St. <hi>John</hi>'s Goſpel is commented upon by many, both <hi>Ancient</hi> and <hi>Modern</hi> Writers, all ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound the words clearly enough without the help of his new crotchet; but if this <hi>Grave Rector</hi> cannot underſtand, <hi>how we ſhould be in Chriſt, by faith and love, and Chriſt in us by his Spirit and Grace, without penetration of dimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, nor how our union to Chriſt ſhould be the ground of fruitfulneſs;</hi> I ſuppoſe his head may be ſomewht dulled, or made heavy, and if ſo, there be <hi>Phyſicians</hi> enow at <hi>London</hi> that can
<pb facs="tcp:56069:20"/> help him. And for his encouragement you may tell him, that when Mr. <hi>W. D.</hi> was trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with an humour of making ſingular expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions of Scripture, Dr. <hi>Sim</hi> of <hi>Huntingdon</hi> gave him ſome Phyſick, and the Phyſick hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wrought, the Gentleman was as <hi>Orthodox,</hi> and expounded Scripture as ſoberly as ever he did in all his life.</p>
            <p>But why do I adviſe this Gentleman to take Phyſick, his head is already marvellous clear, for he ſaith <hi>p.</hi> 197. <hi>That nothing is more eaſie to be underſtood than our <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion and Communion with Chriſt.</hi> He is an happy man indeed if he can underſtand our <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion and Communion with Chriſt, as eaſily as any other thing whatever.</hi> I ſuppoſe our <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion with Chriſt,</hi> is that which the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> calls a <hi>great myſterie,</hi> and am apt to think that <hi>great myſteries</hi> are not <hi>as eaſie to be underſtood as any other things whatever.</hi> Certain I am, that our <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion with Chriſt</hi> is an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion,</hi> and if it be ſo, it cannot be very eaſie to be underſtood; let Mr. <hi>Sh.</hi> review his <hi>Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phyſicks,</hi> and he ſhall find it as hard to attain to a clear and unexceptionable notion of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion,</hi> as of any term, commonly called <hi>Tranſcendental.</hi> Shall I give another taſte what an admirable man Mr. <hi>Sh.</hi> ſeems to himſelf? <hi>King</hi> James <hi>his Tranſlators,</hi> we alway took to be Learned men, never did I hear modeſt man differ from them, <hi>niſi praefatâ veniâ;</hi> but this man of Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticiſmes can find them rendring a place <hi>quite contrary to its ſence.</hi> What place is it? verily <hi>Col.</hi> 2.3. Our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Tranſlation runs thus, <hi>In whom, or wherein, are hid all the treaſures
<pb facs="tcp:56069:20"/> of Wiſdome and Knowledge.</hi> He ſaith this is contrary to the ſence of the place, for it ſhould be, <hi>In whom are all hidden treaſures of Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and Knowledge.</hi> Many had before him ſuggeſted that the words are rather to be ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred this way; but he is I hope the firſt Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficed <hi>Engliſh</hi> Proteſtant that ſaid our <hi>Engliſh Tranſlation</hi> is contrary to the ſence of the place. It is one thing not to <hi>hit</hi> the ſence of a place, another thing to give a tranſlation <hi>contrary</hi> to the ſence of a place. I would faign know what <hi>contrariety</hi> here is in our Tranſlation to the ſence of the place; for I doubt Mr. <hi>Sh.</hi> doth not well underſtrnd what <hi>contrariety</hi> is. His Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, and the Propoſition of our <hi>Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors</hi> may be both true, ſo cannot two contrary Propoſitions. Beſides, if a man ſhould be ſo rigid as to demand of him an argument why our Tranſlation is not to be followed, I doubt he would be at a loſs. Sure I am, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Tranſlation is not ſingular. But here I muſt acquaint Mr. <hi>Sherlock's</hi> hearers with a myſterie: He will read <hi>Col.</hi> 2. as he is appointed by the Kalendar, and will at the 3 <hi>v.</hi> read in whom are hid all the Treaſures of Wiſdom and Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, but they muſt remember that he read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth quite contrary to the ſenſe of the place. And they may do well to get from him a Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue of all other places of Scripture that muſt be underſtood in a ſence contrary to what the words he reads imports. Elſe he and they muſt neceſſarily be of contrary minds. And perhaps if they would not differ from him, they muſt get them not only a new Tranſlation, but a new Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:56069:21"/>
            <p>But I am gone too far, and muſt come back to <hi>pag.</hi> 166. where he ſhews himſelf a <hi>Latitudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narian,</hi> for theſe are his words; <hi>When nothing is made the condition of our communion which is expreſſely forbid by the Laws of our Supreme Lord, we acknowledge his Authority in our ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection to our ſpiritual Guides, and we diſown his Authority in diſowning and affronting theirs.</hi> This ſhould have been proved, and not dicta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; for I am apt to think that if any thing be made an <hi>Article of Communion</hi> which is for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden by a <hi>clear and immediate conſequence,</hi> I am under no obligation to maintain any <hi>communion.</hi> So am I alſo if the omiſſion of any duty which <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath enjoyned be made an Article of my communion. I will never have <hi>Communion</hi> with that <hi>Church</hi> which will allow me <hi>no communion</hi> with her, unleſs I promiſe not to baptize my Son till he come to years of diſcretion, yet I do not believe that Chriſt hath any where <hi>expreſſely enjoyned Infant Baptiſm.</hi> Mr. <hi>Sh.</hi> it ſeems hath more liberty, I envy it not unto him, but rather wonder, how he came by it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 201. He blames ſome men for having <hi>found out a perſon for Chriſt, diſtinct from his God-head and Manhood.</hi> But I ſhould think they had rather been to blame, if they had found out a <hi>perſon not diſtinct from the God-head and Manhood. Godhead</hi> and <hi>Manhood</hi> betoken the two Natures of Chriſt, and if the <hi>Natures</hi> and <hi>Perſon</hi> be not diſtinct, we muſt amend our <hi>Creeds,</hi> and expunge divers perſons out of the black Role of <hi>Hereticks:</hi> Let Mr. <hi>Sh.</hi> try whether he can find out a perſon for Chriſt,
<pb facs="tcp:56069:21"/> not diſtinct from his Godhead and Manhood.</p>
            <p>I might now fall upon that noble and much agitated controverſie concerning the <hi>Imputation of Chriſt's Righteouſneſs,</hi> of which Mr. <hi>Sh.</hi> ſaith a great deal, but he manageth it only a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt one <hi>Dr.</hi> whoſe words and meaning he alſo ſeems to me horribly to pervert and wreſt, and that perſon is about, as I hear, to vindicate himſelf; ſo that I cannot count my ſelf at all concerned to meddle in that affair, as to the merits of the cauſe.</p>
            <p>But there is one thing that this <hi>Author</hi> ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſts about the controverſie, which I cannot but take notice of, <hi>pag.</hi> 239, &amp;c. he ſaith, <q>It is very obſervable that our Saviour in none of his Sermons &amp; Parables, as they are recorded, makes any mention of the imputation of his Righteouſneſs, but exacts from men a Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of their own, never warns them to beware of truſting to their own Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, or of expecting Salvation from their own works; but inſtead of this, ſeverely enjoyns them the practice of an univerſal Righteouſneſs, as the only thing that pleaſeth God.</q>
            </p>
            <p>I eaſily grant (and hope none will deny) that <hi>our bleſſed Lord doth enjoyn the practice of an univerſal Righteouſneſs:</hi> And an <hi>univerſal Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs</hi> (I do not ſay a <hi>perfect</hi> Righteouſneſs) <hi>is neceſſary to our firſt Juſtification.</hi> That Adult perſon who hath not an heart purpoſed and reſolved to give to God and Men (as far as he is able) their due, is for that preſent unjuſtifiable, unpardonable; the continuance of an
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:56069:22"/> upright heart, and the expreſſing of it as oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity ſerves, is neceſſary to the not loſing of Juſtification, and to eternal life. But if Mr. <hi>Sh.</hi> can ſhew me any one place in which our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour inſtead of warning his hearers to beware of <hi>truſting to their own Righteouſneſſes,</hi> or of <hi>expecting Salvation by their own works,</hi> ſevere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enjoyns them the <hi>practice of an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Righteouſneſs, as the only thing that pleaſes God;</hi> I will not only burn all my <hi>Systems,</hi> but alſo confeſs that I have read the <hi>four Goſpels</hi> very negligently and careleſſely. Doth this <hi>Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> in good earneſt think, that nothing pleaſeth <hi>God</hi> but our <hi>own univerſal Righteouſneſs?</hi> yea, doth he not think and believe that our <hi>own per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal Righteouſneſs</hi> all our life long is ſo <hi>ſinfully imperfect,</hi> that God would not be ſo far well pleaſed with it, as to reward it with eternal life, were there not ſomething elſe in the which he is well pleaſed?</p>
            <p>Ob. <hi>Doth Christ any where in all his Sermons make mention of the Imputation of his Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> In ſo many terms he doth not, but when he <hi>bleſſeth</hi> thoſe <hi>who hunger and thirst after righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs,</hi> Dr. <hi>Hamond</hi> thinks that <hi>hungring</hi> may refer to <hi>inherent righteouſneſs,</hi> &amp; ſignifie <hi>an eager deſire of Grace, of Sanctity of Soul;</hi> &amp; that <hi>thirſting</hi> is apportioned to <hi>imputed righteouſneſs,</hi> which he deſcribed to be <hi>Chriſt's righteouſneſs accepted as ours;</hi> or in plainer terms, the <hi>pardon of our ſins, and acceptation of our perſons in Chriſt?</hi> It may be the <hi>learned Dr.</hi> is a little too Critical in this deſcant on our Saviours Metaphors, but
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:56069:22"/> he took it for granted that our Saviour taught his Diſciples of a <hi>twofold righteouſneſs,</hi> elſe he had extreamly forgot himſelf in making ſuch a <hi>Paraphraſe. Imputation of Christ's righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs,</hi> in the ſence in which ſome of our <hi>Biſhops,</hi> and <hi>Epiſcopal Divines</hi> pleaded for it, is not founded either on the <hi>Goſpels</hi> or <hi>Epiſtles:</hi> but take it in the ſence in which thoſe <hi>old Non-conformiſts,</hi> Mr. <hi>Anthony Wotton,</hi> and Mr. <hi>W. Bradſhaw,</hi> explained it, and I will undertake againſt Mr. <hi>Sh.</hi> and all others, to prove it out of the <hi>Sermons and Parables of our Saviour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 240. by way of Parentheſis he lets us know, <q>That he is apt in the firſt place to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire our Saviours Sermons, who was the firſt Author of our Religion, before the Writings of the Apoſtles themſelves, though inſpired men.</q>
            </p>
            <p>If he be but <hi>apt,</hi> and <hi>apt in the firſt place,</hi> I need not much concern my ſelf to enquire what brought him to this <hi>Aptneſs;</hi> I think <hi>Chriſt</hi> is the <hi>onely Author</hi> of our <hi>Religion,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore leave it to him to conſider, why he called him the <hi>firſt Author</hi> of it; but our <hi>Saviour</hi> did no more write the <hi>four Goſpels,</hi> than he did the <hi>Epiſtles.</hi> The <hi>ſame Spirit</hi> that inſpired <hi>Matthew, Mark, Luke, John,</hi> to write the <hi>Goſpels,</hi> inſpired <hi>Paul, Peter, James, John, Jude,</hi> to write the <hi>Epiſtles:</hi> Wherefore, though I know that <hi>Christ</hi> our <hi>Lord</hi> is to be admired above his Servants, yet do not I know why I ſhould read the <hi>Goſpels</hi> with more Admiration or Reverence than the <hi>Epiſtles.</hi> I know no point of <hi>Doctrine</hi> or <hi>Practice</hi> contained in the <hi>Goſpels,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:56069:23"/> which is not alſo contained in the <hi>Sermons</hi> or <hi>Epistles</hi> of the <hi>Apostles:</hi> ſome very weighty and momentous truths which I do not find our <hi>Saviour</hi> to have taught his <hi>Diſciples</hi> in his <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons,</hi> at leaſt not very clearly, I find clearly laid down by the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> in their <hi>Sermons</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated in the <hi>Acts,</hi> or in their <hi>Epistles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 242. <q>We cannot imagine that our Saviour would neglect to acquaint his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples with the neceſſary terms and conditions of Salvation, for his Sermons were to be the Rule of theirs.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Doubtleſs, <hi>our Saviour would not neglect any thing,</hi> for then he had not been Faithfull; and there is no queſtion but he <hi>acquainted his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples with the neceſſary terms and conditions of Salvation,</hi> thoſe they were not before acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with, and thoſe that were neceſſary for that time in which he converſed with them: But that nothing now is neceſſary to be believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by us, which cannot be proved out of the <hi>Goſpels,</hi> I am not he that will affirm, nor yet will I ſay the contrary. Mr. <hi>Sh.</hi> reads to the people that which is commonly called the <hi>Creed of Athanaſius,</hi> and that profeſſeth to contain the <hi>Catholick Faith, which if a man do not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the whole, and undefiled, without doubt he ſhall periſh everlaſtingly;</hi> let him conſider, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he can prove all the <hi>Articles</hi> of that <hi>Creed</hi> out of the <hi>Goſpels,</hi> not calling in the <hi>Epiſtles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 243, 244. <q>It is worth obſerving, that in all the New Teſtament there is no ſuch Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion as the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt, or the Imputation of Chriſts Righteouſneſs,
<pb facs="tcp:56069:23"/> which is very ſtrange, did the whole Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the Goſpel conſiſt in the Imputation of Chriſts Righteouſneſs, that neither Chriſt nor his Apoſtles ſhould once tell us ſo in expreſs terms.</q>
            </p>
            <p>It would be very ſtrange indeed, if there ſhould be any men who ſay, <hi>The whole Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the Goſpel lies in the Imputation of Chriſts Righteouſneſs;</hi> and if there be none ſuch, it is almoſt as ſtrange, that Mr. <hi>Sh.</hi> ſhould encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his own ſhadow; but the <hi>Imputation of Chriſts Righteouſneſs</hi> may be a very important and neceſſary Doctrine, notwithſtanding the <hi>expreſs words of Imputing Chriſts Righteouſneſs</hi> occurre not either in <hi>Goſpels</hi> or <hi>Epiſtles.</hi> This Gentleman I hope owneth the <hi>Satisfaction of Chriſt,</hi> and thinks our Hope is built upon it, now if the <hi>Socinians</hi> ſhould object, (and ſo ſimple be they, that ſometimes they do ſo ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject) <hi>If our hope be ſo built on the Satisfaction of Chriſt, it is ſtrange that neither Christ nor his Diſciples ſhould tell us ſo in expreſs terms;</hi> he would not be long a conſidering what anſwer to return them, and what anſwer he would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to them, may ſuffice to remove his own admiration: In the mean time, let him conſult his <hi>Concordance,</hi> and ſee whether there be no ſuch expreſſion as the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt. There is an Expreſſion very near a kin to it, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.17, 18. <hi>the Righteouſneſs of one,</hi> is <hi>the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt,</hi> mentioned <hi>v.</hi> 17.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 247. <q>No man could believe in Chriſt till he came, <hi>i. e.</hi> could not believe any thing upon his Authority.</q>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:56069:24"/>
            <p>By <hi>coming,</hi> I ſuppoſe he means <hi>coming in the fleſh,</hi> or <hi>being made man;</hi> and let <hi>Chriſtians</hi> Ears judge, whether ſuch a Propoſition as this, <hi>No man could believe any thing on the Authority of Chriſt till he was incarnate,</hi> be not an <hi>ill-ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> Propoſition, whether it ſhould have been put in Print without ſome Explication, and ſome proof. So dull am I, that I can no more ſee an impoſſibility in believing a thing on the Authority of <hi>Chriſt before he came,</hi> than in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving on his Authority <hi>now he is gone</hi> as to his bodily preſence.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 248. <q>That general obſcure Promiſe, <hi>In thy ſeed ſhall all the Nations of the Earth be bleſſed,</hi> is all that ever was revealed to <hi>Abraham</hi> concerning Chriſt.</q>
            </p>
            <p>What dare not a confident man ſay? How knows he that this is <hi>all that ever was revealed to Abraham concerning Chriſt?</hi> He had the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of all the <hi>Revelations concerning Chriſt</hi> that had been made to others, as is probable; alſo he was met by <hi>Melchiſedeck King of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem Prieſt of the most High God,</hi> one of the moſt eminent Types of Chriſt; God made a <hi>cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant</hi> with him, ſealed it with <hi>Circumciſion,</hi> the initiating Sacrament of the <hi>Old Teſtament;</hi> heis called the <hi>Father of the Faithfull;</hi> and yet behold a Divine that dare confidently averre he never had any knowledge of Chriſt, but by <hi>that general obſcure Promiſe, In thy ſeed ſhall all the Nations be bleſſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 249. <q>That Chriſt was to die for the ſins of the World, was more than the Apoſtles of Chriſt themſelves underſtood till after his
<pb facs="tcp:56069:24"/> Reſurrection, though Chriſt had expreſſely told them of it.</q>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Apoſtles</hi> it ſeems, though they had been <hi>ſent to preach,</hi> and had been <hi>told by Chriſt</hi> in expreſs words, that <hi>he muſt die for the ſins of the World,</hi> yet till after the Reſurrection un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood it not. That they <hi>did not</hi> believe this, or were <hi>unwilling</hi> to believe this, or had forgot it when they ſhould have called it to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance to fortifie their hearts, would not ſeem ſo ſtrange; but that they were ſo dull as no<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to underſtand what was expreſſely told them, ſeems very ſtrange. I pray you therefore get Mr. <hi>Sh.</hi> to prove theſe two things to you. 1. That <hi>Chriſt expreſſely told his Diſciples, that he was to die for the ſins of the World.</hi> 2. <hi>That they underſtood not this till after the Reſurrection.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 252. Mr. <hi>Sh.</hi> tells us of a ſtrange En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity, "A natural Faith, founded on natural De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrations "or Moral Arguments; and by this he would have us think that <hi>Abel offered a more acceptable Sacrifice, and Enoch alſo walked with God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Never till this very day, did I ever read or hear of a <hi>Faith</hi> built on <hi>natural Demonſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> or <hi>moral Arguments.</hi> Whatever <hi>aſſent</hi> is built on <hi>natural demonſtrations</hi> is <hi>Science,</hi> what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is built on <hi>moral Arguments,</hi> may be but <hi>Opinion: Faith</hi> I have been taught muſt be founded on <hi>Testimony,</hi> and <hi>divine Faith</hi> muſt be founded on <hi>divine Teſtimony;</hi> that is, on his <hi>Teſtimony</hi> who can neither deceive nor be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived. Mr. <hi>Sh.</hi> defines or deſcribes it to be ſuch <hi>a firm and ſtedfaſt perſwaſion of the truth
<pb facs="tcp:56069:25"/> of thoſe things which are not evident to ſenſe, as makes us confidently expect them.</hi> It is not <hi>evident to ſenſe,</hi> that the next Month there ſhall be a great <hi>Eclipſe</hi> of the <hi>Moon,</hi> yet I have a <hi>firm and ſteadfast perſwaſion of it,</hi> and do <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidently expect it;</hi> is this <hi>Faith,</hi> or doth it make me a <hi>Believer?</hi> I humbly conceive it doth not, and ſhould count my ſelf much engaged to any one who would prove to me, that any one of thoſe <hi>Worthies</hi> mentioned in <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. did ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> Salvation upon any <hi>Faith</hi> but a <hi>Faith</hi> that was built on ſome <hi>Divine Promiſe or Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion concerning Chriſt to come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 260. Mr. <hi>Sh.</hi> tells us, <q>He will ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine thoſe Texts of Scripture which are abuſed by theſe men to ſet up the Perſonal Righteouſneſs of Chriſt as the only formal cauſe of our Juſtification.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Who he means by <hi>theſe men</hi> I cannot tell. Do or did <hi>thoſe men</hi> whom he ſcoffingly calls the <hi>great Acquaintances of Chriſt,</hi> ever bring the <hi>Scriptures</hi> after by him quoted, to prove <hi>Chriſts Rigteouſneſs to be the only formal cauſe of our Juſtification;</hi> if they do not, or did not, then may we conceive that Mr. <hi>Sh.</hi> was ſome night ſcared with a Dream, and writes this part of his Book to be revenged of that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition which affrighted him; if they do or did, I wiſh they had or would cleanſe their Sermons or Diſcourſes from ſuch Ambiguous terms as can miniſter only to vain jangling. I profeſs, I do never in this controverſie hear theſe terms of <hi>material</hi> and <hi>formal cauſe,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſome regret; I muſt ſometimes uſe them,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:56069:25"/> but it is full ſore againſt my will; and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly I take as much care to qualifie them, as the Phyſician doth to correct poyſon. Biſhop <hi>Prideaux</hi> asks, <hi>Quis unquam è noſtris nos per juſtitiam Chriſti imputatam formaliter juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cari aſſeruit.</hi> Yet Biſhop <hi>Davenant</hi> ſaith, <hi>Haec communis eſt noſtrorum omnium ſententia, Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti Obedientiam &amp; Juſtitiam nobis imputatam eſſe formalem cauſam Juſtificationis. De Juſt. Habit.</hi> p. 312. I ſuppoſe the great repute and authority of this <hi>learned Prelate</hi> hath trepan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſome of our Preachers to ſay as he ſaid: Why doth Mr. <hi>Sh.</hi> ſtand pelting at <hi>poor Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticles?</hi> Why doth he not take up his Latine Pen and confute <hi>Davenant?</hi> or if he be more ready and fluent in Engliſh, there's Biſhop <hi>Downham</hi> (the great <hi>Commentator</hi> on <hi>Ramus,</hi> and therefore the more like to undeſtand Logi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal terms) who makes not the <hi>Righteouſneſs imputed,</hi> but the <hi>imputation of it the formal cauſe of Juſtification?</hi> let him try a fall with him, and if he do fairly lay him on his back, the day is his own. But ſtill the <hi>generality</hi> of <hi>Non-conformiſts</hi> are <hi>in ſtatu quo,</hi> out of danger, having never either ſaid or dreamed that Chriſts Righteouſneſs is the <hi>formal-cauſe</hi> of our <hi>juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication.</hi> In putting Mr. <hi>Sh.</hi> upon dealing with the two great Biſhops, you muſt not think that I put him to uſe a weapon at which he hath no skill; for he is a <hi>great School-man,</hi> well ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted not only with their <hi>ſayings,</hi> but with their very <hi>thoughts;</hi> for <hi>p.</hi> 303. he tells Dr. <hi>Owen, He gives ſuch an explication of the term</hi> Quâ, <hi>as the ſubtilest Schoolman of them all ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb facs="tcp:56069:26"/> yet thought of.</hi> Belike he hath ſome ſecret and familiar converſes with the <hi>ſeperate</hi> Souls of the <hi>ſubtileſt Schoolmen,</hi> and correſpondence by Letters with thoſe who are ſtill alive; and they acquaint him what have been and are their thoughts about the particle <hi>Quâ;</hi> and they unanimouſly tell him that it never came into their minds to explicate this Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, <hi>An Embaſſadour eats and drinks as an Embaſſadour;</hi> thus, <hi>He who is an Embaſſadour eateth and drinketh.</hi> If indeed he hath any ſuch way to know what have been the thoughts of the <hi>Schoolmen</hi> concerning <hi>Quâ,</hi> I'le not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict him, nor do I envy him his correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dencies. We begin every day leſs and leſs to ſtand in need of the <hi>Schoolmen,</hi> but I am ſure if the <hi>Schoolmen</hi> that are moſt <hi>ſubtile</hi> have ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted him, that they never thought of any ſuch explication of <hi>Quá</hi> as is before mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, they have played the <hi>Hypocrites</hi> moſt egre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giouſly; for divers and ſundry of them ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining the vulgar <hi>diſtinction</hi> of <hi>Quâ, Speci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficativum</hi> and <hi>Reduplicativum,</hi> do give us juſt ſuch a ſence of the <hi>ſpecificative</hi> As, as is here by Mr. <hi>Sh.</hi> rejected and derided. Thus they ſay, <hi>Plato as he is white</hi> is a <hi>Philoſopher,</hi> is true <hi>ſpecificatively;</hi> as is this alſo, <hi>Chriſt as Man</hi> is to be worſhipped with the Worſhip called <hi>Latria:</hi> But yet both theſe Propoſitions are falſe, <hi>Quâ</hi> being taken <hi>Reduplicatively.</hi> It is like Mr. <hi>Sh.</hi> will ſay, That the <hi>Schoolmen</hi> who do expound <hi>Quâ</hi> to ſuch a ſence, ſpeak very looſely and improperly; and ſo ſay I too, but I am apt to ſuppoſe that they did ſpeak as
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:56069:26"/> they thought; and though I ſhould either re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject this diſtinction, or give a better explica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the members of it, yet if I find any one expreſſing his mind, as many have done before him, I will not throw him my Glove, ot ſend him a challenge, or poſt him up for an <hi>Ignoramus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 326. <q>Now as the Death of Chriſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Croſs, and his Aſcenſion into Heaven, and preſenting his Blood to God in that true Holy Place, did anſwer to the firſt ſprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the Blood under the Law, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed the <hi>Moſaical</hi> Covenant, as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle diſcourſeth <hi>Heb.</hi> 4. ſo his continual in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſion for us in the vertue of his Blood once ſhed, and once offered to God, anſwers to thoſe frequent Expiations by Sacrifice un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Law, eſpecially to that grand Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice on the great Day of Expiation, when the High Prieſt entred into the Holy of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies with the Blood of Beaſts.</q>
            </p>
            <p>So exact a man as Mr. <hi>Sh.</hi> ſhould not have expreſſed theſe things ſo much at random. He ſhould have told us how and when <hi>Christ pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented his blood to God in the true Holy place,</hi> and told us what he means by the <hi>firſt ſprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of blood under the Law,</hi> &amp; how Chriſts <hi>conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual Interceſſions for us anſwer to the frequent Expiations by Sacrifice under the Law, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially to the general Sacrifice on the great day of Expiation;</hi> and if he can give us a true and plain Explication of the whole <hi>Ninth</hi> to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> and not entangle himſelf, nor pull down ſome of the things he had built up, I will
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:56069:27"/> ſay he is a moſt wonderfull man, excelling all the <hi>Syſtematiſts</hi> I know of.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 389. <q>A ſincere Obedience to the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel makes a real Union between Chriſt and us.</q> (I ſhould think that a Purpoſe of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere Obedience makes the Union, and actual ſincere Obedience is an Evidence or Effect of our Union; but let that paſs.) He addes, <q>There is no more need of any Revelation of any private Teſtimony of the Spirit, to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure us that we are united, or that we obey ſincerely, than there is to aſſure us of any thing which is evident to our outward or inward ſenſes.</q>
            </p>
            <p>This will not down without ſome chewing. I never heard of any man that deſired a <hi>teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of the Spirit</hi> for any thing which was <hi>evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to his outward ſenſe:</hi> if it were <hi>evident</hi> that meat was on his Table, Mr. <hi>Sh.</hi> I deem never prayed that the <hi>Spirit would teſtifye</hi> that there was Meat on the Table; but his Heart is deceitfull, the courſe of his Obedience is often interrupted by Acts of ſin, and every Act of Obedience is imperfect; if this notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſincerity of his Obedience be <hi>ſo evident</hi> to him, as what is <hi>moſt evident,</hi> he hath ſuch peace and joy in Believing as few men have, no men that I converſe with; and this Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, <hi>I William Sherlock am really united to Christ,</hi> is to him a <hi>Concluſion de fide.</hi> For thus I frame his Syllogiſm, <hi>Every one that ſincerely obeyes is really united to Chriſt; I William Sherlock ſincerely obey,</hi> Ergo, <hi>I am really united to Chriſt.</hi> The <hi>minor</hi> is as evident
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:56069:27"/> to him, as that his Surplice is white; but ſo I trow is not the <hi>major,</hi> which is a Scripture Propoſition, an <hi>Article de fide,</hi> therefore his Concluſion muſt be <hi>de Fide,</hi> as following the leſs evident Premiſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 399. He takes on him to correct the Notions of ſome men concerning the Love of Chriſt, and ſaith, that with them, <q>The Love of Chriſt is a Love to the Perſon of a Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liever, without conſidering any other Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications, than that he is ſuch an individual Perſon:</q> The meaning whereof he makes to be this, That <q>the Excellency of Chriſts Love conſiſts in this, that he loves for no Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Who the men be that have ſo expreſſed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, I no more know, than I know what the <hi>Pope</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> is doing while I write. All that ever were in any reputation for Learning and Sobriety, ſay, That Chriſt in pardoning a Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liever, and hearing his Prayers, hath <hi>reſpect</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Qualifications; he pardoneth him becauſe he is <hi>meet</hi> for Pardon, becauſe he is a <hi>Penitent,</hi> becauſe he <hi>hateth ſin, confeſſeth, forſaketh ſin,</hi> can <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give</hi> thoſe who have ſinned againſt him; in a word, becauſe he is one, who by vertue of Gods gracious Covenant hath a <hi>right</hi> to Pardon. But why did Chriſt give Repentance to one, and not to another? becauſe he belonged to the Fathers Election: but why did the Father elect this man, and not another? onely becauſe it pleaſed him. Methinks Mr. <hi>Sh.</hi> might allow <hi>God to be mercifull becauſe he will be mercifull,</hi> and to ſhew ſome Acts of Love to <hi>one</hi> Perſon
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:56069:28"/> which he doth not ſhew to <hi>others;</hi> becauſe it <hi>ſeemeth good in his eyes,</hi> and not impute folly to him for <hi>doing with his own what he listeth.</hi> It was an act of love in <hi>Christ</hi> to lay down his life for men; what was the reaſon of this love? what moved him to lay down his life for them, and not for the Angels? It was an act of love in <hi>Christ</hi> to ſend the <hi>Goſpel</hi> to us <hi>Britains,</hi> ſooner by many years than to other Nations; what reaſon can any one give of this love? If the Hiſtories of <hi>God</hi>'s Providence be not all falſe, he hath let the light of his <hi>Goſpel</hi> ſhine among ſome that lived a very lewd and profligate life, by which means they have ſome of them been brought to the knowledge of the Truth into other places, that were better governed; light came not, or at leaſt came not till ſome of thoſe who uſed their Talent of Nature better than moſt, were gone to their graves.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 414, 415. Mr. <hi>Sh.</hi> falls on the bones of Mr. <hi>W. B.</hi> (or perhaps only of ſome ignorant Tranſcriber, or careleſs Printer) for ſome ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions relating to <hi>our love to the Perſon of Christ.</hi> The words quarrelled (though not the only words liable to exception) are theſe. <hi>It is a more excellent thing to love the Perſon of Christ, than the benefits of Chriſt; a more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent thing to have my heart drawn out in love to the Perſon of Chriſt, than to have my heart drawn out in love to him for his benefits. What</hi> (ſaith Mr. <hi>Sh.</hi>) <hi>can be the meaning of all this, but that the excellency and perfection of our love to Chriſt conſiſts in our loving him for no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; the proper object and reaſon of love is Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,
<pb facs="tcp:56069:28"/> to love that which is good for nothing, is the folly and degeneracy of love; and it is as fooliſh and impoſſible a task to love a Perſon, who hath been good to us, not becauſe he hath been good, but for no reaſon. Now this is the caſe here,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>He that will ſpend much time to ſet things right betwixt Mr. <hi>W. Bridges</hi> his Ghoſt, and Mr. <hi>W. Sh.</hi> doth not ſet any very great price upon his time. I for my part am not wont in my communings with my own heart, to vex my ſelf with <hi>Metaphyſical</hi> niceties; If I can but find, that I love <hi>God,</hi> ſo as that I dare not, cannot diſobey him, I am quiet. But Mr. <hi>Sh.</hi> I perceive is profoundly <hi>Metaphyſical,</hi> inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mately acquainted with the writings and thoughts of <hi>Schoolmen,</hi> eſpecially thoſe who were moſt ſubtle among them. I ſhall give him the pleaſure and recreation of propounding ſome difficulties relating to his diſcourſe of love.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Whether <hi>God</hi> did not from all Eternity love himſelf?</p>
            <p n="2">2. Whether in that love he did conſider himſelf as doing good, or beſtowing benefits on him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, or others?</p>
            <p n="3">3. If he did not ſo conſider himſelf, whether he loved himſelf for no reaſon?</p>
            <p n="4">4. Whether there be any goodneſs in what is <hi>meerly poſſible,</hi> but <hi>ſhall never</hi> be?</p>
            <p n="5">5. If there be any goodneſs in what is <hi>meerly poſſible,</hi> whether the ground of <hi>God</hi>'s love to it be good, it doth to <hi>himſelf,</hi> or <hi>others?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">
               <pb facs="tcp:56069:29"/>6. What is the <hi>Ground, Object, Reaſon</hi> of <hi>God</hi>'s love to the <hi>Creature?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. Whether the <hi>Creature</hi> be bound to love the <hi>Creator</hi> more than the <hi>Creature?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8. Whether the <hi>benefits</hi> we receive from <hi>God,</hi> be not <hi>created</hi> beings?</p>
            <p n="9">9. Whether if the <hi>benefits we receive from God,</hi> be the <hi>ſole</hi> or <hi>chief ground</hi> of our loving <hi>God,</hi> we do not either love the <hi>Creature</hi> more than the <hi>Creator,</hi> or not love the <hi>Creator at all?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe are knots which Mr. <hi>Sh.</hi> can eaſily un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye; for what is there that can be difficult to him who hath all his <hi>Philoſophy</hi> at his fingers end?</p>
            <p>In the mean time I muſt conclude theſe ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertiſements, which you had never ſeen, if ſo be thoſe on the firſt Chapter put into the form of a Letter at your importunity, had not been far beyond the time allowed by you or me, deteined in the Countrey. Upon the whole I think, Mr. <hi>Sh.</hi> ſhould not have thrown ſo many ſtones at <hi>other mens</hi> writings, till he had took care to make <hi>his own</hi> leſs faulty. He might if he had pleaſed have choſen other <hi>Subjects</hi> and <hi>Perſons</hi> on whom to exerciſe his <hi>Juvenile</hi> Pen. I verily believe his book will not occaſion any one man to live a better life, or to look on <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naticks</hi> with the worſe eye.</p>
            <p>You will ſay all this while I have ſaid very little in defence of thoſe whom Mr. <hi>Sh.</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnes.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:56069:29"/>
            <p>I confeſs I have ſaid but a little, and yet I have ſaid more than I intended, and more than was needful; for what if every paſſage in ſome mens popular diſcourſes will not bear a ſevere tryal by the <hi>Rules of Art?</hi> is this any diſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement to the cauſe of <hi>Non-conformiſts?</hi> Cannot I find paſſages in the <hi>Homilies</hi> of the <hi>Fathers,</hi> that would make good ſport, if any one would be at the pains to lay them to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and play upon them? Or have any of our late ſo much <hi>famed Writers</hi> againſt the <hi>Papists,</hi> took ſo much care to put out their Books, as never to ſtand in need of a very can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>did Reader? He that <hi>Preacheth oft,</hi> and <hi>Printeth much,</hi> may do no more than what he thinks himſelf in Conſcience bound to do; but it is a thouſand to one, he will in many things lay himſelf open.</p>
            <p>Ay, but the men whom Mr. <hi>Sh.</hi> pincheth, do profeſſedly avow ſuch principles as <hi>naturally tend to make men bad,</hi> or <hi>hinder and retard their progreſs in true holineſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> If his deſign were only to expoſe opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions that <hi>naturally tend to make men bad, or,</hi> &amp;c. it was very laudable; and if his <hi>Conſcience</hi> do clearly witneſs that he had no other deſign, he hath the leſs to anſwer, though he hath failed in the managing of his deſign. But,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Before he charge any opinion, he ought fairly to ſtate, and candidly to repreſent that opinion. This I ſeldome find him to do, and if I had ſaid I never found him ſo to have done, I ſhould not <hi>lye,</hi> though perhaps I might be <hi>miſtaken.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb facs="tcp:56069:30"/>2. He ought never to charge any man with thoſe <hi>conſequences of an opinion</hi> which he knows to be <hi>diſowned</hi> and <hi>diſavowed</hi> by him; for though he who writes againſt an <hi>opinion,</hi> is to burden it with all the <hi>conſequences</hi> which do naturally flow from it; yet is not he who maintains the <hi>opinion,</hi> to be repreſented forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, as one who <hi>avows</hi> all thoſe conſequences. Indeed it were to no purpoſe to diſpute againſt any man by urging the <hi>conſequences</hi> flowing from his <hi>opinion;</hi> if he did <hi>own</hi> thoſe conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, in vain it would be, I mean as to the man himſelf who <hi>owns</hi> the conſequences, though perhaps not in vain, as to every one of thoſe whom he had proſelyted to his opinion.</p>
            <p n="3">3. He ſins againſt <hi>God</hi> and his <hi>Neighbour</hi> every time he draws a <hi>bad</hi> ſenſe out of words that are capable of a <hi>good</hi> ſence. How often he hath polluted his Conſcience this way, may eaſily be diſcerned; I ſhall give one inſtance for all, <hi>pag.</hi> 379, 380. he layeth it to the charge, <q>of ſome men, that they do ſo mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie the attainments of Hypocrites, who ſhall never go to Heaven; that it is impoſſible for any ſanctified man to do more than an Hypocrite may do.</q> If there be any men who ſo do, they are to be withſtood, as <hi>adverſaries to all Chriſtian Conſolation in this world.</hi> But who are the men that ſo do? why, Mr. <hi>Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard</hi> doth ſo; and will the <hi>Conſcience</hi> of this <hi>Miniſter of the Goſpel</hi> ſuffer him to charge that upon men which is found only for ought ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears in Mr. <hi>Shepeheard.</hi> If Mr. <hi>Shepeheard</hi> through a zeal without knowledge, have indeed
<pb facs="tcp:56069:30"/> made thoſe things common to <hi>Hypocrites,</hi> which are proper only to <hi>Sound Believers,</hi> and <hi>ſincere Chriſtians,</hi> he muſt bear his own bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den; and leſs underſtanding. Readers are to be cautioned that they prejudice not themſelves by his writings; but what is this to others who contributed nothing to the making or Printing his Book, and perhaps never ſaw his Book? So <hi>pag.</hi> 37, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> He tells us of <q>an acquaintance with the Perſon of Chriſt, which if we will believe ſome men, is the only fountain of ſaving knowledge, this acquaintance he after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards makes to be ſuch an acquaintance as is not to be got or attained to by the Goſpel; yea, which is contrary to that acquaintance we can get from the Goſpel.</q> Are there ſome men who make <hi>ſuch an acquaintance with Chriſt's Perſon, the ſole fountain of ſaving knowledge?</hi> I never ſaw any ſuch, never read of any ſuch, and hope there are none ſuch in the world; Mr. <hi>Sh.</hi> thinks there be: and how doth he prove it? Why, <hi>J. O. D. D.</hi> in a Book Entituled, of <hi>Com. with Father, Son, and Holy Ghost,</hi> hath ſome expreſſions which if they be ſet on the Rack, and conſtrued to a ſence that it is manifeſt he never intended, may ſeem to hold forth <hi>ſuch an acquaintance with the Perſon of Christ;</hi> and this is ſufficient to this <hi>Rector of St. George Buttolph-Lane,</hi> to charge on a party of men ſo vile a principle; this is ſufficient to warrant him to call Mr. <hi>Shepeheard</hi> (who 'tis like never heard of Dr. <hi>Owen,</hi> and to be ſure was dead before his Book of <hi>Communion</hi> came forth) by way of Scorn, a great acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of Chriſt.</p>
            <pb n="58" facs="tcp:56069:31"/>
            <p>Well, but let us imagine yet Mr, <hi>Sher.</hi> had charged Mr. <hi>Shepheards</hi> ſayings only on Mr. <hi>Shepheard,</hi> and try whether he hath done him no wrong in what he chargeth upon him. I ſay he hath manifeſtly, laying to him ſuch faults as it doth not appear he was ever guilty of. Mr. <hi>T. S.</hi> ſtands charged as one that ſo <hi>magnifies the attainments of Hypocrites, that it is impoſſible for any ſanctified man to do more than he may do.</hi> To make this good, he is brought in anſwering the pleas which ſeveral Hypocrites make for themſelves: and Mr. <hi>Sher.</hi> ſuppoſeth the ſame man to make all theſe pleas for himſelf, which is not fair or juſt. Let's hear the <hi>Pleas,</hi> and the <hi>Anſwers to them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Plea. <hi>I have left my ſins I once lived in, and am now no Drunkard, no Swearer, no Lyar.</hi> Mark, it is not ſuppoſed that he hath left all the ſins he once lived in.</p>
            <p>Anſw. <hi>Be waſhed from all the mire (the pollution of the world) and yet be a Swine in God's account.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This I ſay is a truth, a man may be <hi>waſhed from the pollution of the world, and yet be a Swine in God's account;</hi> that is, his outward converſation may be ſo altered, as that he ſhall ceaſe to act and practiſe thoſe things which the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> calls the <hi>Pollutions of the world,</hi> and yet his <hi>heart</hi> be ſtill <hi>unclean,</hi> and ſo remain <hi>a Swine in Gods account,</hi> for God eſteemeth him a <hi>Swine</hi> who is not <hi>cured</hi> of his <hi>ſwiniſh diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition,</hi> though he be ſo <hi>restrained</hi> as that he doth not <hi>wallow in the mire.</hi> Ay, but Mr. <hi>T. S.</hi> proves this from 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.20. which is <hi>point
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:56069:31"/> blank contrary to what he Affirms.</hi> That is, it is <hi>point blank contrary,</hi> if we will take Mr. <hi>Sh</hi>'s word, but we will look for a proof before we yield any point blank contrariety.</p>
            <p>Plea. <hi>I Pray, and that often.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Anſ. <hi>So thou mayest, and yet never be ſaved,</hi> Iſa. 1.11. <hi>To what purpoſe is the multitude of your Sacrifices?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That Mr. <hi>S. H.</hi> may Maſter this Objection, he ſuppoſeth the man who ſo pleadeth to live, <hi>a blameleſs, innocent, honest, ſmooth life;</hi> and then replyeth, that Sacrifices when offered by <hi>ſuch,</hi> are ſure to <hi>great</hi> purpoſe, and that the want of ſuch a life, made thoſe <hi>Sacrifices abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable to God.</hi> But it may be queſtioned whether Mr. <hi>T. S.</hi> ſuppoſed the man who <hi>prayed often,</hi> to be of a <hi>blameleſs, innocent, honest, ſmooth life;</hi> yet if he had made that ſuppoſition, his anſwer may be <hi>good</hi> and <hi>perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent;</hi> for if a man's life be <hi>blameleſs,</hi> &amp;c. if it be not ſo with <hi>relation to God and Men,</hi> and in <hi>every thing,</hi> his Prayers may avail nothing.</p>
            <p>Plea. <hi>But I faſt ſometimes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Anſ. <hi>So did the Scribes and Phariſees twice a week.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> It was to <hi>devour Widows houſes,</hi> which was not the faſt of an honeſt innocent man. It is then granted, that a <hi>very groſs Hypocrite may fast ſometimes,</hi> which is enough to juſtifie Mr. <hi>T. Sh.</hi> But where did Mr. <hi>Sh.</hi> learn that the <hi>Scribes and Phariſees did faſt twice a week to devour widows houſes;</hi> or that on thoſe <hi>fasting dayes they made longer Prayers than other men?</hi> Yea, how doth he prove that the <hi>Phariſees de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:56069:32"/> widows houſes?</hi> In <hi>Mark</hi> and <hi>Luke</hi> this is charged only on the <hi>Scribes.</hi> And though it be charged on the <hi>Phariſees, Matth.</hi> 23.14. yet there is ſome queſtion made by learned men whether that Verſe be not thruſt into <hi>Matthew.</hi> Mr. <hi>Sh.</hi> ſhall do well to correct <hi>Grotius</hi> and <hi>Brugenſis,</hi> to aſſert the <hi>Authentity</hi> of thoſe <hi>Greek Copies</hi> which our <hi>Tranſlators</hi> follow; and then he may with more confidence ſay the <hi>Phariſees made long Prayers to devour widows houſes,</hi> yet if he will ſay ſo before he hath taken ſuch pains, I will not reprove him; for I am no advocate of <hi>Phariſees.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Plea. <hi>I hear the Word of God, and like the beſt Preachers.</hi> Anſ. <hi>So did the ſtony Ground, who heard the Word with joy, and for a ſeaſon believed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Sh</hi>'s reply to this, is wonderfully deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered in theſe words, <hi>This had been well, and a good ſign of grace if it had continued.</hi> That is, the <hi>diſpoſition</hi> which was in the <hi>hearers</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to the <hi>ſtony ground,</hi> was a <hi>good ſign of Grace</hi> whil'ſt it <hi>continued,</hi> but by <hi>not continuing</hi> it became <hi>no ſign of Grace:</hi> Before the <hi>ſcorch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Sun</hi> came, the <hi>ſtony ground</hi> was <hi>good ground,</hi> as well as <hi>ſowed with good ſeed.</hi> What is the reſult of this? why,
<q>
                  <l>—<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ltima ſemper</l>
                  <l>Expectanda dies homini eſt, ſanctúſque vocari</l>
                  <l>Ante obitum nemo, ſupremáque funera debet.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Suppoſe a man doubting of his condition, ſhould come to Mr. <hi>Sh.</hi> and tell him, that he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyceth
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:56069:32"/> in the Word, and believeth; he will anſwer, this is a <hi>good ſign of grace if it conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue;</hi> but how ſhall I know whether it <hi>will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue?</hi> that will appear when tribulation or perſecution comes, becauſe of the Word of the Kingdom, till then hope the beſt. How well this will ſatisfie a man that is concerned for his Soul, we may eaſily gueſs; none of the <hi>Non-conformiſts</hi> whom he ſo much ſcorns, would have ſent away a doubting Chriſtian with ſo <hi>unſatisfactory</hi> an anſwer, they can eaſily out of God's Word, lay down Characters by which the <hi>joy</hi> and <hi>faith</hi> of an <hi>Hypocrite</hi> may be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned, before the <hi>Hypocrite</hi> quite falls from either.</p>
            <p>Plea. <hi>I read the Scripture often.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Anſ. <hi>So did the Phariſees, who were ſo perfect in the Bible, that Chriſt needed but to ſay, It hath been ſaid of old times, for they knew the Text without intimation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If theſe be Mr. <hi>T. S</hi>'s words (which having not the book by me, I cannot examine) he much miſtook himſelf; for as it may be que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtioned whether <hi>Chriſt</hi> ever ſaid, <hi>it hath been ſaid of old times;</hi> ſo it is certain that that form of ſpeech which he uſed, however to be ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, was ſpoken not to the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees,</hi> but to his <hi>own Diſciples,</hi> whom we muſt account <hi>generally</hi> good. But the <hi>Divinity</hi> is good, he who reads the Scripture often may be an <hi>Hypocrite?</hi> what is it that Mr. <hi>Sh.</hi> objects or adverteth. Firſt, he ſcoffingly ſaith, <hi>Men of prodigious Memories certainly, better than any Concordance.</hi> Doth he indeed think
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:56069:33"/> that they muſt be <hi>men of prodigious Memories</hi> that can <hi>tell the Text without intimation;</hi> if ſo, the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Nation abounded with many <hi>prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies,</hi> for that there were many in it, who if they had been at hand were better than any <hi>Concordance</hi> for the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Text, I ſuppoſe he doth not doubt. His anſwer is ſtill behind, <hi>Though Knaves may read the Scriptures, and be never the better for it; yet good men may read it to good purpoſe, and therefore I hope reading the Scripture is no argument that a man is a Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite, becauſe the Phariſees were.</hi> This <hi>hope</hi> is ſuch as he need not be aſhamed of, but he ſhall do well to take ſhame to himſelf, for endeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to put a man famed for Piety, into a Fools Coat, to ſee whether he can make people laugh at him. O! that he would before it be too late, commune with his own heart, and ſearch the <hi>Scriptures</hi> to ſee whether this <hi>Drollery</hi> becomes a <hi>Preacher.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Plea. <hi>I am grieved and ſorrowful, and repent of my ſins.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Anſ. <hi>So did Judas.</hi> What ſaith Mr. <hi>Sh.</hi> to the caſe of <hi>Judas?</hi> why, that he <hi>hanged himſelf,</hi> and that indeed was no <hi>repentance unto life.</hi> Indeed the <hi>repentance</hi> of <hi>Judas</hi> was no <hi>repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance unto life;</hi> nor did Mr. <hi>T. S.</hi> ſay it was, but brought it as an inſtance of a repentance <hi>not</hi> unto life. And I wiſh all pretending to be the <hi>Sons of the Church,</hi> would well conſider what the <hi>Homily</hi> ſaith of <hi>Judas</hi> his <hi>repentance:</hi> 2d. <hi>part of the Sermon of Repentance.</hi> It might perhaps move ſome of them to alter their ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions about the Nature of Repentance,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:56069:33"/> and not take up with ſuch a Repentance as is ſo far ſhort of what <hi>Judas</hi> did. In the mean time I am glad to find Mr. <hi>Sh.</hi> acknowledging that <hi>Judas</hi> hanged himſelf, becauſe the <hi>immortal Hugh Groot</hi> goes quite another way, as alſo do <hi>Heinſius, De Dieu,</hi> Dr. <hi>Lightfoot;</hi> it ſeems this <hi>Rector</hi> is not alway out of conceit with that Tranſlation he reads to the People. I wiſh by minding him, that <hi>late Criticks</hi> deny <hi>Judas to have hanged himſelf,</hi> I have not laid a ſtone of offence in his way.</p>
            <p>Plea. <hi>But I love good men and their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>An. <hi>So did the fooliſh Virgins.</hi> What jeſt hath Mr. <hi>Sh.</hi> to break upon this? (for he is not in the mood of giving ſerious replies) why this, <hi>The fooliſh Virgins ſlept, and ſuffered their Lamps to go out, which I hope all that love good men do not.</hi> If he hope there are <hi>any</hi> good men who do not ſleep, he hopes there be ſome wiſer than <hi>any</hi> of the <hi>five wiſe Virgins;</hi> as for not letting their Lamps go quite out, Mr. <hi>Th. S.</hi> will allow him not only to <hi>hope</hi> it of ſome good men, but alſo to <hi>affirm</hi> it of every good man.</p>
            <p>Plea. <hi>God hath given me much knowledge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Anſ. <hi>That thou mayeſt have, and never be ſaved.</hi> Mr. <hi>Sh.</hi> denyes not this; but adds, <hi>If a blameleſs honeſt man have the keeping of this knowledge, it is never the worſe for him;</hi> which if you mark it well, is an huge Commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>good knowledge,</hi> that a man is <hi>not the worſe for it.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:56069:34"/>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1 line">
                  <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>Anſ. <hi>So did the Jews, whom yet Chriſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demneth.</hi> Here Mr. <hi>T. S.</hi> ſtumbled, and Mr. <hi>Sh.</hi> muſt needs call to all <hi>England</hi> to take notice of it; But the anſwer though unhappily expreſſed, is ſufficient to ſhew that a man may ſtrictly keep a day of Divine Inſtitution, and yet be of the number of thoſe whom <hi>Chriſt</hi> condemns. But hath not Mr. <hi>Sh.</hi> committed a greater miſtake in ſaying, that to keep the Lords Day ſtrictly is one good thing, which doth well in the company of more? ſuch a Speech would formerly have been eſteemed <hi>Puritanical,</hi> and it may be this, notwithſtanding he could like well enough of a <hi>Book of Sports.</hi> 2. In im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying that <hi>with other things, it will juſtifie a man;</hi> for as I think, it is <hi>God,</hi> and not the <hi>Obſervation of the Lords Day</hi> that <hi>juſtifieth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I am aſhamed to obſerve how in the remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of <hi>p.</hi> 382, and <hi>pag.</hi> 383. throughout Mr. <hi>Sh.</hi> ſhews his teeth, and knoweth not where to bite; juſt like a man that wiſheth his adverſary had errors to be confuted, and were ſorry he could find none.</p>
            <p>That <hi>a man may think he hath a good heart to God, and yet deceive himſelf,</hi> which is all that Mr. <hi>Shepeheard</hi> ſaith, he cannot deny, but wiſheth he had ſaid, <hi>that a man who thinks he hath a good heart towards God, muſt needs be mistaken;</hi> and then he would ſay, <hi>the whole Doctrine concerning marks and evidences were at an end.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It may perhaps be worthy a little obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, what Mr. <hi>Sh.</hi> ſaith; to a <hi>diſtinguiſhing</hi> mark
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:56069:34"/> betwixt a <hi>regenerate</hi> and an <hi>unregenerate</hi> man. <hi>An unregenerate man,</hi> ſaith T. S. <hi>let him go ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo far, do never ſo much, yet he lives in ſome one ſin or other.</hi> This I ſay is a good Rule for a man to judge himſelf by: He that allows himſelf in no known ſin either of <hi>Omiſſion</hi> or <hi>Commiſſion,</hi> is a <hi>regenerate</hi> man: Every <hi>unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate</hi> man allows himſelf in ſome <hi>known</hi> ſin of <hi>omiſſion</hi> or <hi>commiſſion.</hi> A <hi>Regenerate</hi> perſon hates every known ſin, and ſincerely endeavours to avoid all known ſin, ſo <hi>doth</hi> no <hi>unregenerate</hi> man, ſo <hi>can</hi> no <hi>unregenerate</hi> man doe: no man not born of <hi>God,</hi> loves <hi>God</hi> above all; there is ſomething he loves above <hi>God,</hi> and what the effect of not loving <hi>God</hi> above all muſt needs be, who knows not? Mr. <hi>Sh.</hi> it ſhould ſeem doth not, for he ſaith, this is very ſtrange, <hi>That let an unregenerate man go never ſo far, and doe never ſo much, yet he lives in ſome one ſin or other.</hi> If it ſeem <hi>ſtrange, very ſtrange,</hi> I cannot help it; but a little <hi>Chriſtian Philoſophy</hi> will take away the admiring Humour.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, It is manifeſt that Mr. <hi>Sh.</hi> thruſts out his ſting againſt thoſe who have written no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing (taken notice of by him) that can be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to hurt or hinder Godlineſs. He men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions <hi>Thomas Vincent,</hi> p. 144. cenſureth the <hi>prettineſs and fantaſtical Wit of an Exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion made by him:</hi> What is the <hi>Exhortation?</hi> why the <hi>Exhortation</hi> is directed to his Hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, <hi>To chooſe Chriſt for their Husband, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is Rich, Beautifull and Kind, and hath all the Properties of an excellent Husband. This</hi> he ſaith, <hi>would ſound better in a Popiſh Nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nery,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:56069:35"/> than among ſuch pretenders to Reformation.</hi> One mans Exhortation doth not pleaſe him, but he cannot content himſelf to declare his diſpleaſure againſt one man; we preſently hear of <hi>pretenders to Reformation, not ſo gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous ſuitors for Chriſt as the Papiſts.</hi> To the reproach of my ſtupidity, I cannot ſee what <hi>prettineſs</hi> or <hi>fantaſticalneſs is in this Wit,</hi> if <hi>wit</hi> it muſt be called. I ever took it for grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that in <hi>ſound</hi> Converſion a man is taken in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a <hi>conjugal Relation with Chriſt,</hi> and that if any man ſo related to <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſhould fall into an Act of <hi>Idolatry,</hi> he ſhould commit <hi>ſpiritual A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dultery,</hi> and would provoke God to jealouſie. This <hi>young Divine</hi> is ſo illuminated that he can <hi>correct Magnificat,</hi> and ſpy a <hi>beam</hi> in Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions ſo uſual among the greateſt <hi>Clerks,</hi> and ſo agreeable to <hi>Scripture;</hi> let us ſee what Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery he hath made. <hi>The Church is Chriſts Spouſe, and every Chriſtian is a member of that Society which Chriſt owns for his Spouſe: He is a great Enemy to Polygamy, and hath but one Spouſe, as he hath but one Body, but one Church.</hi> If Mr. <hi>Vincent</hi> ſhould grant all this to be true, his Exhortation is not at all ſpoyled; Maids are ſtill to be perſwaded to <hi>chooſe Chriſt to be their Husband,</hi> onely it ſeems they muſt firſt chooſe to be <hi>members of the Church,</hi> and then they ſhall be <hi>parts</hi> of the <hi>Spouſe of Chriſt.</hi> But I ſhould think, that as his <hi>Majeſty</hi> by being <hi>King of England, Scotland, Ireland,</hi> is <hi>King</hi> to <hi>every</hi> Perſon in theſe three Kingdoms; ſo Chriſt by being <hi>Husband</hi> to his <hi>Church,</hi> hath the Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of an <hi>Husband</hi> to <hi>every</hi> member of the
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:56069:35"/> 
               <hi>Church.</hi> It is the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> that is call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the <hi>Spouſe</hi> in the <hi>Canticles,</hi> and the <hi>Wife</hi> of the <hi>Lamb</hi> in the <hi>Revelations;</hi> but why is ſhe ſo called, but becauſe ſhe is a <hi>collection</hi> of ſuch <hi>men</hi> and <hi>women</hi> as are <hi>married</hi> or <hi>eſpouſed</hi> to him. The <hi>Church</hi> which is married to <hi>Chriſt</hi> is alſo <hi>married</hi> to his <hi>Father,</hi> is ſo his <hi>Wife</hi> that ſhe is alſo his <hi>Mother,</hi> and yet <hi>Chriſt</hi> is as great an Enemy to <hi>Inceſt</hi> as <hi>Polygamy.</hi> Let us leave it to <hi>Julian</hi> to <hi>ſcoffe</hi> at theſe <hi>Titles</hi> and <hi>Relations;</hi> and for our own parts, let us <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire</hi> at the <hi>condeſcenſions</hi> of <hi>Divine love,</hi> and conceive of things <hi>ſpiritual ſpiritually,</hi> ſo ſhall we be accounted worthy to be <hi>called to the Marriage of the Lamb,</hi> and be brought by him into his Fathers Houſe, which he hath prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for all that fear him.</p>
            <p>I have now done, and deſire you to keep theſe Papers to your ſelf; or if you will needs ſhew them to Mr. <hi>Sh.</hi> to conceal my Name; for I love not to enter into the Liſts with any man, and he hath already Adverſaries enow. And if you will, you may pleaſe to acquaint him with the <hi>miſadventures</hi> of ſome men of <hi>wit,</hi> but of no great <hi>judgement</hi> in <hi>Divinity. Verge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi> was a <hi>witty</hi> man, elſe he had not been made <hi>Legate</hi> to <hi>Clement</hi> the ſeventh, and <hi>Paul</hi> the third; he ſetting himſelf to write againſt the <hi>Apoſtates</hi> of <hi>Germany,</hi> became by reading their Books, their Convert, and ſo quite loſt the Hope he had of a <hi>Cardinalſhip: Pighius</hi> adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turing to read <hi>Calvin</hi> about <hi>Juſtification,</hi> with a deſign to refute him, became a <hi>Calviniſt</hi> in
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:56069:36"/> point of <hi>Juſtification,</hi> and that did not help him to Preferment. A <hi>worthy</hi> &amp; <hi>Right Reverend</hi> Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, now one of his <hi>Majeſties Biſhops,</hi> preaching when he was young, for a Friend of yours and mine, very elegantly diſcourſed againſt the <hi>Impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the active Righteouſneſſe,</hi> in that ſence which looks a little too like <hi>Antinomianiſm,</hi> our Friend told him, he had delivered but his ſence, yet blamed him for that being ſo <hi>young,</hi> he would ſo <hi>peremptorily</hi> declare himſelf in a point wherein it was poſſible he might live to be of <hi>another</hi> mind. He replyed, That it could not be, he ſhould alter his Mind in that matter; but ſetting himſelf afterwards to preach at large about <hi>Juſtification,</hi> he moſt <hi>profeſſedly pleaded</hi> for the <hi>Imputation of the Active Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs,</hi> and of that mind he is ſtill. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend to his Reading, three <hi>Non-conformiſts,</hi> Mr. <hi>Fox, De Chriſto gratis juſtificante;</hi> Mr. <hi>Anthony Wotton, De Reconciliatione,</hi> &amp;c. Mr. <hi>William Bradſhaw, De Juſtificatione.</hi> Bid him alſo conſider, whether if the <hi>Parliament</hi> ſhould meet, they might not find leiſure enough to cenſure his Diſcourſe, as they did Mr. <hi>Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagues,</hi> who in vain pleaded for himſelf, That he he had writ againſt the <hi>Puritans,</hi> and was left alone to ſuffer, though others had inſtiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him to write. The <hi>Commons</hi> of <hi>England</hi> will ſcarce endure to find the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of the Church of <hi>England</hi> ſtruck at, though it be through the ſides of Dr. <hi>Owen</hi> and Dr. <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> Nor can I think, that the <hi>Reverend</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> of our <hi>Church</hi> read this Book of
<pb facs="tcp:56069:36"/> Mr. <hi>Sh</hi>'s. without a Frown in their Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heads; common Fame is more than ordinarily falſe, if ſome of them have not manifeſted their diſlike of it. Theſe things you may if you pleaſe ſuggeſt to your Author. Let <hi>Brotherly Love</hi> continue betwixt you and</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your, &amp;c.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
